Alright, I'd like to get started,
好的，我要开始了，
can anyone hear me?
有人能听到我说话吗？
Yep loud and clear.
是的，声音很大，而且清楚。
Alright, so today my plan is
好的，那么今天我的计划是，
for first I want to spend a few minutes
首先，我想花几分钟
re-emphasizing some points from the lecture last week on thread switching,
重新强调上周课程中关于线程切换的一些观点，
because they turned out to be important points,
因为它们是重要的观点，
and I would spend most of the lecture talking about something called coordination
我会用这节课的大部分时间讨论一个称为协作的东西，
which is the larger term for xv6 sleeping wakeup mechanism
它是 xv6 休眠唤醒机制的大的术语，
and particularly I'm going to talk about the lost wakeup problem.
我要特别谈一下唤醒丢失的问题。
Alright, so, one, one point I want to just mention again is that,
好的，有一点我想再提一下，
is the fact that xv6 whenever anything calls switch
是 xv6 当有东西调用 swtch ，
to switch from one thread to another,
要从一个线程切换到另一个线程，
usually from a kernel thread to the scheduler thread,
通常从内核线程到调度器线程，
it's always preceded by an acquire of this process's lock.
它总是在预先获取这个进程的锁。
So process requires this lock call swtch,
所以进程获取这个锁调用 swtch ，
which always switches into the scheduler
它总是切换到调度器，
and it's the scheduler that releases the lock.
而调度器释放那个锁。
In fact almost always the sequence looks more like this
事实上，顺序是这样的，
or a process who wants to go to sleep for some reason,
或者一个进程因为某种原因想要休眠，
it's yielding the CPU for waiting for something
它让出 CPU 等待某些东西，
and it acquires a lock on itself,
它会获取自己的锁，
it sets its state,
设置自己的状态，
and there's a number of different states,
这里有很多状态，
what we see we saw last week was,
我们上周看到的，
set state to runnable instead of running,
将状态从运行中设置为可运行，
and then call swtch
然后调用 swtch ，
or sched which itself calls swtch.
或者调用 sched 来调用 swtch 。
And that you know this switch basically switches threads over into the scheduler thread,
这个 swtch 是将线程切换到调度器线程，
which so as previous call to swtch,
与之前调用 swtch 一样，
this scheduler thread returns.
这个调度器线程返回。
And then this was scheduler thread calls release on the lock of the process,
然后调度器线程释放这个进程的锁，
that's just yielded the CPU.
让出CPU 。
The reason for this, just to repeat, is that,
这样做的原因，只是重复一下，是因为，
the acquisition of this lock on the process
获取进程上的锁
prevents the scheduler on a different core
会阻止不同核心的调度器，
from from looking right at this point in time,
在这个时间点上查看，
and saying that, oh this thread is runnable and trying to run it,
然后说，这个线程是可运行的，并试图运行它，
because every other core maybe running a scheduler loop,
因为每个其他核心也许运行一个调度器循环，
which is continually looping over the process table,
它不断地在进程表上循环，
looking for runnable threads,
寻找可运行的线程，
so any one of them may see that this thread is runnable,
所以它们中的任何一个都可能看到这个线程是可运行的，
if we hadn't acquired the process lock,
如果我们没有获取进程锁，
so the fact that we acquired the process lock means
所以我们获得进程锁意味着，
that the other schedulers, before they even look at a process of state,
其他调度器，在查看进程状态之前，
must acquire its lock.
必须取得它的锁。
So we know after this acquisition,
所以我们知道这次获得之后，
no other threads going to look at the lock.
没有其他线程会查看该锁。
We can't give up the lock here though,
我们不能在这里放弃锁，
we can't give up the lock before calling swtch,
我们不能在调用 swtch 之前放弃锁，
that is this thread acquires the lock,
也就是说，这个线程获取锁，
but it can't give it up,
但它不能放弃它，
because if we did,
因为如果我们这么做了，
then right after we gave it up,
那么在我们放弃之后，
some other core scheduler would probably start running this process,
某个其他核心的调度器可能会开始运行这个进程，
even though the thread is currently running on this core.
即使那个线程当前正在这个核心上运行。
And having two cores run the same thread, using the same stack,
让两个核心运行相同的线程，使用相同的堆栈，
is would cause a pretty instant crash.
会造成瞬间的崩溃。
And therefore the process acquires lock
所以，进程获取锁，
and does release it at called swtch
在调用 swtch 时释放它，
and different thread, namely the scheduler thread actually releases the lock,
不同的线程，即调度器线程释放锁，
at a point after this thread has completely stopped using its own stack,
在这个线程完全停止使用其自己的堆栈之后，
so at this point, it's okay for another core scheduler running this thread,
这时另一个内核的调度器运行这个线程是可以的，
because the thread is now no longer running
因为线程现在不再运行，
and has given up given up the processor.
并且已经放弃了处理器。
Okay, so that's an important point
好的，这是很重要的一点，
and it'll come up in a few minutes,
它几分钟后会出来，
it's one of the many constraints
这是诸多限制之一，
on the design of the sleep wakeup coordination scheme.
在 sleep wakeup 协同机制的设计上。
Any questions about this holding of the p->lock across switch?
关于 swtch 持有 p->lock ，有什么问题吗？
Yeah, if.
是的，如果。
Yes.
是的。
When we have multiple cores,
当我们有多个核心时，
the only reason they're able to have the same view of the lock is,
它们能看到相同的锁的唯一原因是，
because there's a single shared physical memory system right?
因为只有一个共享的物理内存系统，是吗？
That is correct.
这是正确的。
So, is there like implementations
那么，有没有这样的实现，
where there's weird file systems,
其中有奇怪的文件系统，
that can guarantee this [adversity]
可以保证这一逆境，
so we can [lock].
这样我们就可以使用锁。
If you buy two computers, then they don't share memory, right,
如果你买两台计算机，那么它们不会共享内存，对吧，
so that's one way to do if you buy two separate computers,
所以，一种方式是如果你购买两台计算机，
then they won't share memory
这样它们就不会共享内存，
and we won't have any of these problems.
我们就不会有任何这些问题了。
It's just that the way processor chips look,
只是从处理器芯片的角度来看，
these days, there's always multiple cores on a single processor chip
如今，单个处理器芯片上总是有多个核心，
and so the hardware just is built to have multiple cores sharing the same memory system.
所以，硬件被构建为让多个核心共享相同的内存系统。
Oh I see, thanks.
我明白了，谢谢。
Okay, so that's one point.
好的，这是一点。
Another point,
还有一点，
I don't think I've mentioned yet,
我还没有提到，
has to do with the fact that
与一个事实有关，
in xv6, a process is not allowed to hold any other lock when it calls swtch.
在 xv6 中，进程在调用 swtch 时不允许持有任何其他锁。
A process is required to hold p->lock when it called swtch,
进程调用 swtch 时需要持有 p->lock ，
but it is forbidden to hold any other lock when it calls swtch,
但当它调用 swtch 时，禁止持有任何其他锁，
so this is another important constraint
所以这是另一个重要的限制，
on the design of many things,
关于很多东西的设计，
including how sleep is going to work.
包括休眠是如何工作的。
So now let me lay out the reasoning for this,
让我来描述一下这件事的理由，
so it's no other locks, when you call swtch.
这是当你调用 swtch 时，没有其他的锁。
A scenario, sort of illustrating why this is this rule has to be enforced,
这个方案说明了为什么这条规则必须强制执行，
and this is a rule that,
这是一条规则，
you know, if you're, extending,
如果你扩展，
you know you're a programmer developing the xv6 kernel
你是开发 xv6 内核的程序员，
have to follow this rule along with many other rules.
必须遵守这条规则以及其他一些规则。
So the justification for this rule
那么这条规则的正确性，
supposing we have process one or the kernel thread for process one
假设我们有进程一，有进程一的内核线程，
and it acquires some lock,
它会获取一些锁，
you know not impressive, but just some lock,
这并不稀奇，只是一些锁，
maybe it's using the disk or using the uart to console
可能它正在使用磁盘或使用 uart 控制台，
and acquire some lock.
并且获取一些锁。
And supposing it did then,
假设它发生了，
give up the CPU by calling swtch or yield or sched or something,
通过调用 swtch 或 yield 或 sched 或其他方法放弃了 CPU ，
while still holding this lock.
但是仍然持有这把锁。
So now p1 holds lock,
所以现在 p1 持有锁，
this lock held, but it's not running.
持有锁，但是并没有运行。
And imagine also for a moment
想象一下，
that we're on a machine with just a single core.
我们在一台只有一个核心的机器上。
So there's only one core,
所以只有一个核心，
the process one called swtch which transfers the scheduler,
进程一调用 swtch ，转移调度器，
the scheduler sees aha process two's kernel thread is waiting to run
调度器看到进程二的内核线程在等待运行，
and so the scheduler switches the process,
所以调度器切换进程，
starts running process to two, switches to process two
开始运行进程二，切换到进程二，
and supposing process two for whatever reason,
假设进程二，不管出于什么原因，
maybe it also wants to use the disk or use that uart or something
或许它还想使用磁盘或 uart 之类的东西，
and it calls acquire on the same lock,
它对同一个锁调用 acquire ，
so we have a second acquire of this lock,
所以我们第二次获取这把锁，
it's the same the same lock.
这是同一把锁。
Of course, the lock already held,
当然，锁已经持有了，
so this acquire can't get it,
所以这个 acquire 拿不到它，
these are spin locks,
这些是自旋锁，
so what this actually causes to happen is that
所以，这会导致，
process two inside acquire will just sit in a loop
进程二内部的 acquire 会在一个循环中，
spinning waiting for the lock to be released.
旋转等待锁被释放。
And acquire won't return
而且 acquire 不会返回，
and since acquire doesn't return,
既然 acquire 不会返回，
process two can't, doesn't have a chance,
进程二不能，没有机会，
even though it may be willing to yield the CPU when it's done later on,
即使它愿意在完成的时候让出 CPU ，
it doesn't get a chance to,
它没有机会这样做，
because the acquire doesn't return until the lock is released.
因为 acquire 在锁释放之前不会返回。
You know, but the only way the lock could be released is
但是唯一能释放锁的方法是，
if process one resumes execution,
如果进程一恢复执行，
and presumably later, it's correctly, it doesn't have terrible bugs in it,
并且可能稍后，它是正确的，没有严重的 bug ，
it was going to call it was intending to release this lock right,
它会打算释放这个锁，
but it hasn't happened yet,
但这还没有发生，
because it's called swtch
因为它调用了 swtch ，
and process two is spinning waiting for the lock,
而进程二正在旋转，等待这个锁，
so this is a deadlock, right,
所以这是一个死锁，
and it will just cause the system to freeze.
这会导致系统冻结。
And while I described this in the context
我描述这个的上下文是，
of a machine with a single CPU, a single core,
一台只有一个 CPU ，一个核心，
you can construct scenarios
你可以想象，
that using multiple locks would cause this same kind of deadlock
使用多个锁将导致相同类型的死锁，
on a machine with multiple cores.
在一台有多个核心的机器上。
And so as a result, we have a general prohibition in xv6,
所以，在 xv6 中有一个普遍的限制，
that you're not allowed to hold spin locks across the swtch.
不能在 swtch 时持有锁。
Any questions about this rule?
对于这条规则，有什么问题吗？
There's a question in the chat Robert.
聊天中有个问题，罗伯特。
Oh, would you have a timer interrupt, switch to p1 which resolves the deadlock.
能否有一个定时器中断，切换到 p1 来解决死锁？
Okay so, yet, it does turn out,
好吧，那么，确实是这样，
so we're running, both all the stuffs running in the kernel right,
所以所有这些东西都运行在内核中，
you know acquire release which you know only so kernel code,
acquire release 都是内核代码，
so not running in user space,
不是运行在用户空间中，
but indeed a timer interrupt could occur
但确实定时器中断可能会发生，
and xv6 is actually allows timer interrupts to happen
而且 xv6 允许定时器中断发生，
in while running kernel code, system call code
在运行内核代码，系统调用代码时，
and in fact if you look at the kernel trap code
事实上，如果你查看内核陷阱代码，
or whatever it is in trap.c,
或者不管在 trap.c 里的什么，
you'll see that if a timer interrupt happens,
你会看到，如果发生定时器中断，
while xv6 is executing the kernel,
当 xv6 执行内核时，
it will call yield.
它会调用 yield 。
So if a timer interrupt could happen,
所以如果定时器中断发生，
while we're running acquire here,
当我们在这里运行 acquire 时，
then actually we would be saved,
那么我们就会得救，
because we call yield switch back here
因为我们调用 yield ，返回到这里，
and hopefully p1 would then resume and eventually release the lock,
希望 p1 恢复并最终释放锁，
however, for reasons that were explained in a previous lecture,
然而，由于上一节课已经解释过的原因，
acquire turns off interrupts before it starts to wait for the lock,
acquire 在开始等待锁之前关闭中断，
because we absolutely for other reasons,
出于其他原因，
cannot afford to have an interrupt happen while we're holding a lock,
不能承受在我们持有锁的同时发生中断，
because that would cause a different kind of deadlock.
因为那会导致另一种死锁。
It's the interrupt handler, needed to use, needed to acquire the lock,
它是中断处理程序，需要获取锁，
that this acquire had possibly just acquired,
这个 acquire 可能是刚刚获得的，
so if you look at the code for acquire xv6,
所以，如果你查看 xv6 中的 acquire 代码，
you'll see the first thing it does is turn off interrupts and then spins
你会看到它做的第一件事就是关闭中断，然后旋转
and you may wonder those, why doesn't it spin and then turn off interrupts
你可能会想，为什么它不是旋转，然后关闭中断，
and the reason is that would allow a short period of time to occur
原因是这将允许短时间内发生，
in which the lock is held, but interrupts weren't disabled
锁被持有，但是中断没有被禁用，
and again device interrupted that time might cause a deadlock.
再一次，如果这个时间段发生设备中断，可能会导致死锁。
So, unfortunately,
所以，不幸的是，
this other requirement that we leave interrupts off
这是另一个要求我们关闭中断，
while we're spinning waiting for lock
当我们旋转等待锁时，
prevents the timer interrupt from going off
防止定时器中断关闭，
and therefore prevents process two from yielding back to process one.
并且防止了进程二回到进程一。
That's a good question.
这是个好问题。
Okay so another question,
好的，另一个问题，
can I repeat how deadlocks are avoided?
我可以重复一下如何避免死锁吗？
Oh, deadlocks are avoided in xv6 by prohibiting this,
在 xv6 中通过禁止这个来避免死锁，
xv6 code is not allowed to acquire any lock other than p->lock,
xv6 代码不允许获取 p->lock 以外的任何锁，
and then call swtch
然后调用 swtch ，
and if you look at the code for swtch,
如果你看一下 swtch 的代码，
there's actually some checks in swtch,
在 swtch 里有一些检查，
that are equivalent to checking that no locks are held other than p->lock.
检查除了 p->lock 之外没有锁被持有。
So the problem with this is this code,
所以问题是这个代码，
if it occurred in the xv6 kernel would be illegal
如果它发生在 xv6 内核中，将是非法的。
and would could easily cause a deadlock,
很容易造成死锁，
so it's forbidden.
所以这是被禁止的。
As that answered the question?，Okay.
这回答了这个问题吗？好的。
Other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Okay, okay, so keep this rule
好的，记住这条规则，
and previous need to hold p->lock across switch in mind,
以及预先在 swtch 中持有 p->lock ，
because they'll come up again
因为它们会再次出现，
in our discussion of how sleep and wakeup work.
在我们讨论睡眠和唤醒是如何工作的时候。
Alright new topic, coordination,
好的，新主题，协调，
which really means sleep/-, the.
就是 sleep/wakeup 。
We've heard a lot about locks
我们听说过很多关于锁的事，
and locks are fantastic for situations
锁在某些情况下是很棒的，
where different threads really want to not be aware
不同的线程不必担心，
and not have to worry about or think about what other threads are up to,
而不必担心或考虑其他线程在做什么，
we hold locks and share data,
我们持有锁并共享数据，
that means we just never have to worry about the possibility
这意味着我们不必担心这种可能性，
that some other lock is is or maybe not, who knows, using that data,
其他的锁是或不是使用这些数据，
because the lock, so it causes things to happen one at a time,
因为锁导致一次只发生一件事，
but when you're writing threaded code,
但是当你编写线程化代码时，
there are also situations where you explicitly want to wait for some specific event
也有某些情况，你需要等待特定的事件，
where you want different threads to interact.
你希望不同的线程进行交互。
So, for example, supposing, we have pipes
比如，假设我们有管道，
and we got a reader and a writer right,
我们有读取者和写入者，
if I'm reading a pipe,
如果我正在读取管道，
and there's nothing currently to read in the pipe,
而当前在管道中没有要读取的内容，
I want to be able to wait for any other process to write data to the pipe,
我希望能够等待任何其他进程将数据写入管道，
I want to wait for this sort of pipe is not empty event.
我想等待管道不是空的事件。
Similarly if I'm reading the disk, or writing the disk.
同样的，如果我正在读取磁盘，或正在写入磁盘，
If I'm reading the disk,
如果我在读取磁盘，
then I want to be able to tell the disk controller,
然后我希望告诉磁盘控制器，
look, please read a particular block on the disk,
请读取磁盘上的某个块，
it may take a long time milliseconds,
可能需要很多毫秒，
long long time before the disk finally finishes the read,
在磁盘完成读取完成之前需要很长时间，
especially if it has to seek and rotate
特别是如果它必须寻找和旋转，
and the process is doing the read needs to be able to wait for that specific event,
正在读取的进程需要等待这个特定事件，
we want to wait for the disk read to complete.
我们希望等待磁盘读取完成。
Similarly you may have noticed,
同样地，你可能已经注意到，
when you're programming, that a unix program can make the wait system call.
当你编程的时候， unix 程序可以进行 wait 系统调用。
And what wait does is
而 wait 所做的是，
it causes the calling process to wait, until any of its children exit,
它使调用进程等待，直到它的任意子进程退出，
so here we have the parent process intentionally waiting
所以，这里我们故意让父进程等待，
for some event sort of caused by another process.
等待某种由另一个进程引起的事件。
So these are all situations where a process needs to wait for a specific event
所以，这些都是进程需要等待事件的情况，
either typically IO or another process,
通常是 IO 或另一进程，
sort of declaring that something specific has happened.
表示发生一些特殊的事情。
And coordination is the sort of tool
协调是一种工具，
that helps us solve these kind of problems
帮助我们解决这类问题，
or implement these kind of requirements
或者实现这些要求，
and coordination is totally fundamental,
而且协调是很基础的，
just just like with locks, coordination is another fundamental tool
就像锁一样，协调是另一个基本工具，
for writing threaded programs
用于编写线程化程序，
and it comes up all the time.
并且它总是出现。
Alright, so, how could we have a process or a thread wait for this kind of event,
好的，那么，我们怎么让一个进程或一个线程等待这种事件，
so one possibility is extremely straightforward one is
一种可能的非常简单的方法是，
just a busy wait to loop,
就是忙等待循环，
so you could imagine.
你可以想象。
And we'll discard this as a bad idea in a moment,
我们马上就会把它当作一个坏想法扔掉，
but let's say we want to read from a pipe,
但是假设我们想要从管道中读取，
we just write a loop in the pipe read function
我们在管道读取函数中编写了一个循环，
that says you know while you know the pipe buffer is empty,
也就是 while 管道缓冲器是空的，
we're gonna do absolutely nothing, right,
我们什么都不会做，
now we're gonna let sit in this loop going around around in this loop,
现在我们在这个循环中的旋转，
until maybe some other thread on another core
直到另一个线程或另一个核心
writes into the buffer and makes it not empty
写入缓冲区，使其不为空，
and then this loop will finish
然后这个循环就会结束，
and then we'll return the data
然后我们会返回数据，
or whatever it is we're supposed to do with the data.
或者无论我们如何处理这些数据。
So you imagine writing code like this
所以，你可以想象这样编写代码，
and actually there is a little bit of,
实际上有一点，
there may be you know small amount of code like this,
可能像这样有很少的代码，
like if you know that the thing you're waiting for is extremely likely to happen
如果你知道你等待的事情极有可能发生，
and a tenth of a microsecond,
十分之一微秒，
let's say this may be the best way to wait for it,
这种等待可能是最好的方式，
so typically this is done with some kind of device hardware.
所以，对于一些设备硬件通常是这样完成的。
When you ask the device hardware to do something,
当你要求设备硬件执行某些操作时，
you know it will always complete that task in a tiny amount of time,
你知道它总是会在很短的时间内完成这项任务，
just sitting in a short loop can be the right answer.
只是在一个短的循环里，可能是正确的选择。
But if this might take a long time milliseconds,
但是，如果这可能需要很多毫秒长的时间，
or you just don't know how long right,
或者你不知道时间有多长，
maybe it's going to be ten minutes
可能需要 10 分钟，
before whatever process is writing the pipe actually writes anything,
在任何进程写入管道之前，
then we don't want to spin there and waste CPU time,
那么我们就不想在那里旋转，浪费 CPU 时间，
which could be used to find more digits of pi or something else useful,
它可以用来找到更多的 π 的数字或其他有用的东西，
we want to give up the CPU instead.
相反，我们想放弃 CPU 。
And only we want some way to give up the CPU like swtch,
我们想要像 swtch 一样放弃 CPU ，
but actually regain the CPU when the event we care about has actually occurred
但在我们关心的事件发生时重新获得 CPU ，
and it's that that coordination is all about techniques
这种协调是一种技术，
to give up the CPU until the condition, the event that we're waiting for has actually occurred.
放弃 CPU ，直到条件出现，我们等待的事件发生。
And again sleep and wakeup,
再一次， sleep/wakeup ，
there's a number of different coordination primitives
有多种不同的协调原语，
that people have invented over the years.
在很多年中，人们发明的。
And xv6 in common with many flavors of Unix,
xv6 与许多 Unix 的风格相同，
uses something called sleep and wakeup.
使用一种 sleep/wakeup 的东西。
Okay, alright, with this background,
好的，在这样的背景下，
I'd like to switch to a looking at code in xv6.
我想切换到查看 xv6 的代码。
Alright, so I just shared my screen,
好的，我刚分享了我的屏幕，
let me know if the screen share did on work.
如果屏幕共享起作用了，请让我知道。
Okay, I have in preparation for this lecture,
好的，我已经为这次课程做了准备，
rewritten some of the code in the uart driver,
重写了 UART 驱动程序中的一些代码，
that's the serial driver that xv6 uses to read and write characters from the console,
这是 xv6 用来从控制台读写字符的串行驱动程序，
so I have this function uartwrite,
所以我写了这个 uartwrite 函数，
which when a program like the shell prints its prompt or produces any other output,
当像 shell 这样的程序打印提示符或产生任何其他输出时，
that makes a write system call
会使用一个 write 系统调用，
and in my slightly modified version of xv6
在我稍微修改的 xv6 版本中，
that write system call ends up with a call to uartwrite,
write 系统调用以 uartwrite 的调用结束，
in the uart driver
在 uart 驱动中，
which actually writes the characters in this loop one by one to the uart hardware.
将这个循环中的字符逐个写入 uart 硬件。
And this is written in a sort of classic device driver style.
这是以一种经典的设备驱动程序风格编写的。
You'll see code like this in many device drivers.
你会在许多设备驱动程序中看到这样的代码。
Okay, so one of the things that's going on here is
好的，这里发生的一件事是，
that the uart hardware can only accept one character for transmission at a time,
uart 硬件一次只能接受一个字符进行传输，
and so the way this code has to look,
所以这段代码需要查看的，
typically have lots of characters you want to write,
通常你有很多想要写入的字符，
it can write a character to the uart hardware,
它可以向 uart 硬件写入字符，
and it needs to wait for the uart hardware
它需要等待 uart 硬件
to say yes I finished sending that character,
是的，我已经把那个字符发送完了，
I'm ready for a new one
我准备好接受一个新的字符了，
and then the driver can write a new one,
然后驱动可以写入一个新的，
a new character the next character to output,
下一个要输出的的新的字符，
because this hardware can operate very slowly,
因为这个硬件运行起来非常慢，
like maybe only a thousand characters per second,
可能每秒只有一千个字符，
the amount of time we have to wait between characters can be very long,
我们在字符之间等待的时间可能非常长，
in milliseconds in a long, long time, on modern computer,
以毫秒为单位，在现代计算机上是很长的时间，
it's you know a billion cycles a million cycles maybe,
可能是十亿个，百万个机器周期，
which a huge amount of work could be done,
这可以做大量的工作，
so we'd really prefer not to just spin
所以，我们不希望只是旋转，
waiting for the uart to finish sending each character.
等待 uart 完成每个字符的发送。
We like to have a better way,
我们想要有更好的方式，
and so in fact, xv6 has a better way like most operating systems,
事实上，像大多数操作系统一样， xv6 有更好的方式，
the uart hardware will raise an interrupt after it's finished sending each character,
uart 硬件在完成发送每个字符后引发中断，
and so we have not just this write routine,
所以我们不仅仅有这个写入例程，
we'll see uart driver has an interrupt routine
我们将看到 uart 驱动程序有一个中断例程，
which I think trap.c calls
我认为会调用 trap.c ，
when the uart hardware raises an interrupt to say that it's finished
当 uart 硬件发出中断通知已完成时，
and the interrupt routine checks that uart
中断例程检查 uart ，
to read one of the memory mapped registers in the uart hardware
读取 uart 硬件中的一个内存映射寄存器，
to look for the flag that says I'm done transmitting,
查找表示已经完成发送的标志，
which is this LSR_TX_IDLE flag,
应该是 LSR_TX_IDLE 标志，
and if that flag set,
如果设置了这个标志，
then the interrupt routine actually sets this flag in memory,
那么中断例程在内存中设置该标志，
and makes this wakeup call
然后调用这个 wakeup 调用，
which will calls the uartwrite,
这将调用 uartwrite ，
whatever thread is in uartwrtie,
不管 uartwrite 是哪个线程，
to return from its sleep here
从这里的睡眠中恢复过来，
and attempt to send a new character.
并尝试发送新字符。
So the game is that,
所以流程是这样的，
if a thread needs to wait for something
如果线程需要等待某些东西，
and here we are, we need to wait for the uart hardware
在这里，我们需要等待 uart 硬件
to be willing to accept a new character
能够接受新字符，
to call sleep waiting for a specific condition, usually,
通常调用 sleep ，并等待特定条件，
and when the condition is fulfilled,
当条件满足时，
code that realizes the condition is fulfilled what called wakeup.
实现该条件的代码调用 wakeup 。
So these sleeps and wakeups are paired.
所以这些 sleep 和 wakeup 是成对的。
And sleep will look at the implementation by and by,
sleep 会查看实现情况，
but sleep does a number of things
sleep 会做很多事情，
and then calls swtch in order to give up the CPU.
然后调用 swtch 来放弃 CPU 。
One thing to notice is
需要注意的一件事是，
that the wakeup and sleep have to be linked together somehow,
wakeup 和 sleep 必须以某种方式联系在一起，
that is we call wakeup,
就是我们调用 wakeup ，
we really only want to wakeup threads that are waiting for the specific event,
我们只想唤醒等待特定事件的线程，
that we realize has happened
我们[意识到]已经发生，
and so sleep and wakeup take this argument
所以 sleep 和 wakeup 都有这个参数，
which is called the sleep channel,
它被称为睡眠通道，
it's wakeup supplies the very same value here, that we're passing to sleep,
这里 wakeup 支持同样的值，我们传给 sleep 的值，
sleep and wakeup actually don't really look,
sleep 和 wakeup 不会真的查看，
don't care what these these,
不在乎这些是什么，
they just take 64 bit values here,
它们在这里只取 64 位的值，
they don't care what they are really,
它们不在乎它们是什么，
the only thing that's going on is that,
唯一发生的事情是，
when if we sleep on that particular sleep channels, particular wait channel,
当我们在特定的睡眠通道，等待通道上睡眠时，
we want to wakeup to pass the very same value here,
我们希望 wakeup 传递与此相同的值，
in order to show that indicate which sleepers it wants to wakeup.
表示它想要唤醒哪些睡眠者。
Any questions about this interface?
关于这个接口，有什么问题吗？
Okay.
好的。
So there's a question just to clarify
所以有一个问题需要确认，
the process is not woken up every for every character that's written.
进程不是对每个写入的字符唤醒。
Okay, let's see,
好的，让我看看，
in this driver that I've specially hacked for demonstration purposes,
在这个为了演示而改写的驱动程序中，
there's an interrupt per character,
每个字符都有一个中断，
so the the the way uartwrite works is that
所以 uartwrite 的工作方式是
for each character
对于每个字符，
that is in this while for each character in the buffer character supposed to write,
在这个 while 中，对于缓冲区中要写入的每个字符，
we wait here in this loop,
我们在这个循环中等待，
until the uart is ready to accept one more character,
直到 uart 准备好接受另一个字符，
we write one more character,
我们再写入一个字符，
we set this done flag to zero,
我们把这个完成标志设置为 0 ，
and go back and wait typically in sleep until the done flag is one.
返回，在 sleep 中等待，知道完成标志为 1 。
And then after the uart finished sending this character,
然后，在 uart 发送完这个字符之后，
it'll interrupt and the interrupt routine will set done to one and do the wakeup,
它会中断，并且中断例程完成标志设置为 1 ，并进行唤醒，
so in fact there is a wake- sleep and wakeup
所以，这里有一个 sleep wakeup ，
in an iteration of the loop for every single character
对于每个字符的循环的迭代中，
and more the uart is actually capable of sending some number,
uart 实际上有能力发送一些数量，
like 4 16 or something characters at a time,
比如 4 个或 16 个或更多字符，
so a more efficient driver
所以，更高效的驱动程序
would would hand 16 characters to the uart per iteration of this loop
在这个循环的每次迭代中向 uart 传递 16 个字符，
and there'd be an interrupt every 16 characters
每 16 个字符有一个中断，
and higher speed devices are typically like ethernet drivers,
并且更高速的设备，比如以太网驱动器，
typically accept many more bytes than that per interrupt.
通常每个中断接收多得多的字节。
Alright.
好的。
Okay, so this is just an illustration of what the interface looks like.
好的，这只是接口概况的展示。
Sleep and wakeup are nice,
sleep 和 wakeup 很好用，
because for one reason they're nice, they're relatively flexible,
它们好用的一个原因是，它们相对灵活，
sleep wakeup don't really care what it is uart to.
sleep wakeup 并不关心 uart 是什么。
Yeah, you can.
是的，你可以。
You don't have to tell sleep what you're waiting for,
你不必告诉 sleep 你在等什么，
you don't have to tell wakeup what event happened,
不必告诉 wakeup 发生了什么事，
you just need to have these matching sleep channel 64 bit values.
你只需要使用匹配的睡眠通道 64 位值。
However, there's one interesting property of the sleep interface,
然而， sleep 接口有一个有趣的属性，
we have to pass it a lock here,
我们要在这里传递一个锁，
there's a second argument, this lock argument
第二个参数，这个锁参数，
and there's a big story behind why sleep takes this second argument.
为什么 sleep 需要第二个参数，背后有一个很大的故事。
And I'm gonna explain what's going on,
我会解释这是怎么回事，
but the high level picture is,
但更高层次的画面是，
that it's not doesn't seem to be possible
这似乎是不可能的，
to design a sleep that is completely ignorant of what it is you're trying to wait for.
设计一种完全不知道你要等待的是什么的 sleep 。
It's hard to write a sort of general purpose sleep,
很难写出一种通用的 sleep ，
that simply sleeps waiting for some specific event
它只是在睡眠，等待一些特定的事件，
and this is danger,
这很危险，
which we'll see in a moment called lost wakeups
我们稍后会看到，称为 lost wakeups ，
that just about every coordination mechanism
每种协调机制，
has to grapple with somehow and deal with somehow.
必须以某种方式处理这种问题。
And then the sleep interface, this fact, we have to pass a lock
而 sleep 接口，我们必须传入一个锁，
is sort of a little bit of ugly implementation,
是一种有点丑陋的实现，
leaking through into the interface in a way,
以某种方式泄漏到接口中，
I'll explain in just a moment.
我稍后会解释。
Yeah, I'll explain,
好的，我会解释，
this is a question,
有一个问题，
why do we need the done flag and the sleep channel?
为什么我们需要完成标志和睡眠通道？
I will hold on to that question,
我会抓住这个问题，
I'll explain that in five or ten minutes.
在五分钟或十分钟后解释这个问题。
Okay, so before explaining why it is that sleep is doing with this lock,
好的，在解释为什么 sleep 要用这个锁之前，
I actually want to talk a bit
我想讨论一下，
about what the implications would be if we had a simpler sleep,
如果我们有一个更简单的 sleep 会有什么影响，
that didn't have didn't take that extra lock argument.
它不需要额外的锁参数。
So.
所以。
Alright so.
好的，那么。
And the topic here is lost wakeups,
这里的主题是 lost wakeups ，
that's the problem gonna describe now.
这是现在要描述的问题。
so, suppose that the interface was
所以，假设接口只是
just sleep on this arbitrary channel value with no second argument,
sleep 在任意的通道上，没有第二个参数，在没有第二自变量的该任意信道值上，
you can't make this work,
这个不能正常工作，
so I'm actually gonna call this broken_sleep.
所以我把这叫做 broken_sleep 。
And you could imagine,
你可以想象，
if we didn't know better that,
如果我们不是更清楚地知道这一点，
sleep like this could simply set the state of the process to this special sleeping value
这样的 sleep 可以简单地将进程状态设置为这个特殊的休眠值，
which says I don't want to run anymore, I'm waiting for a specific event
表示不想继续运行了，我在等待一个特定的事件，
and then if you look at the xv6 implementation of sleep,
如果你看一下 sleep 的 xv6 实现，
you'll see it does this among other things,
你会看到它还做了其他事情，
we need to record this special sleep channel value,
我们需要记录这个特殊的睡眠通道值，
so that a future call to wakeup can realize that we're actually waiting for the thing,
这样将来的 wakeup 调用就可以意识到我们在等待的东西，
that the wakeup is waking us up for,
wakeup 为我们唤醒，
so you could imagine a sleep and would be broken,
你可以想象 sleep 被打破，
that really just did this,
它只做了这些，
I guess you'd have to take acquire this process is locked also.
我想你也必须获取这个进程的锁。
And then of course, [] wakeup.
当然，然后[] wakeup 。
And this really is pretty much how wakeup works,
这是关于 wakeup 是如何工作的，
we want to wakeup all the threads
我们想唤醒所有的线程，
that are waiting on that are called sleep with this particular channel value,
它们正在等待，使用了特定的信道值调用 sleep ，
so we're just going to say,
所以我们只是，
you know for each p and the process table,
for each p 和进程表，
if the state if it's sleeping,
如果状态是睡眠状态，
and it's sleeping on the channel that we're waking up,
它睡眠在我们要唤醒的信道上，
then set the state to runnable,
然后将状态设置为可运行的，
actually modular [], this is pretty much what a wakeup does.
实际上模块[]，这就是 wakeup 所做的。
Okay, so, some alternate [] [] would be nice,
好吧，这个替补的[]会更好，
if sleep and wakeup with this simple.
如果 sleep 和 wakeup 都这么简单。
Let me demonstrate though,
让我来演示一下，
let me demonstrate.
让我来演示一下。
Well, before I go back to the xv6 code,
在我回到 xv6 代码之前，
let me just outline
让我来概述一下，
how you would use this sleep and wakeup in the uart driver
你将如何在 uart 驱动程序中使用这个 sleep 和 wakeup ，
and this is sort of a repeat of what we've already seen,
在某种程度上，是我们已经看到的情况的重复，
but using this slightly simpler interface.
但是使用这个稍微简单一点的接口。
You would have.
你会有。
And indeed the driver does this you have this done flag,
驱动完成这个，有完成标志，
then uartwrite,
然后 uartwrite ，
you know would say for each character in the buffer,
对于缓冲区中的每个字符，
and then which check this done flag
然后检查完成标志，
just say while not done, go to sleep,
还没有完成，就去睡觉，
and then pass that channel whatever was tx_chan or something,
然后传递一个信道，不管是 tx_chan 还是别的，
doesn't really matter.
其实并不重要。
Okay and then we're gonna send c to the uart,
好的，然后我们将 c 发送给 uart ，
and set done equals zero right.
并将 done 设置为 0 。
And then the interrupt routine just sets it done flag is equal to true,
然后，中断例程将其完成标志设置为真，
and of course wakeup.
当然还有 wakeup 。
So this is how we could use this simplified broken_sleep.
所以，这就是我们如何使用这种简化的 broken_sleep 。
Alright, so this is really broken_sleep.
好的，这其实是 broken_sleep 。
With this is missing though is locking,
这里，缺少的是锁，
so actually, both both of these routines
所以，实际上，两个例程，
for both the write routine and the interrupt routine absolutely have to lock.
写入例程和中断例程的都必须使用锁。
And one reason is that,
其中一个原因是，
this done flag, anytime we have shared data,
这个完成标志，任何时候我们共享数据时，
we really need to put a lock around the shared data,
我们都需要对共享数据加锁，
and the other reason is that,
另一个原因是，
actually I didn't put it in here,
实际上我没有把它放在这里，
but both the interrupt routine and the write routine
但是中断例程和写入例程
need to access the hardware that uart hardware itself
都需要访问 uart 硬件本身，
and typically it's an error,
通常这是一个错误，
unless you're very very clever,
除非你非常非常聪明，
it's an error to have two threads
让两个线程
concurrently try to read and write the memory mapped hardware registers,
同时读写内存映射硬件寄存器是错误的，
so we need a lock around in both of these subroutines
所以，我们需要在这两个子例程中都设置一个锁，
in order to avoid both racing access on done and racing accesses to the hardware.
为了避免对完成标志竞争访问和对硬件的竞争访问。
So the question is where should we put the locks in.
所以问题是我们应该把锁放在哪里。
It's it's easy in the interrupt routine,
在中断例程中很容易做到，
we're gonna lock our lock at the beginning,
我们在开始就加锁，
whatever the lock I think its called uart_tx_lock or something
不管是什么锁，我想它叫 uart_tx_lock 或别的什么，
and we're gonna unlock at the end.
然后我们在最后解锁。
So the interrupt routine just takes a lock and releases it,
所以中断例程只是获取一个锁并释放它，
the puzzle is where to put the locks in the uart routine.
难题是如何在 uart 例程中放置锁。
One possibility is
一种可能是，
that uartwrite could hold the lock
uartwrite 可以持有的锁
for the entire sequence of trying to send a character each character.
对于发送每个字符的整个序列。
So we could acquire the lock here, and unlock here.
所以，我们可以在这里获取锁，在这里释放锁。
So lock and unlock it at the beginning and very end processing each character,
所以，加锁和解锁在处理每个字符的开头和结尾，
so why, why does this definitely not work.
那么为什么这肯定行不通呢。
One reason is that
其中一个原因是
the only way we can get out of this loop is that
我们走出这个循环的唯一方法是，
the interrupt routine sets done to one,
中断例程将完成标志设置为 1 ，
but if we hold this lock for this entire sequence in it,
但是如果我们在整个序列中持有这个锁，
the interrupt routine also needs to lock
中断例程也需要锁，
and so it will sit here spinning waiting for the lock,
所以它会在这里旋转等待锁，
because we hold the lock
因为我们持有锁，
and aren't going to release it until done is set,
并且在设置完成之前不会释放它，
but done can only be set when the interrupt routine is actually able to get the lock,
但是完成标志只能在中断例程获得锁时才能设置，
so we cannot just simply hold the lock
所以我们不能简单地持有锁
across the entire sequence of sending each character.
在发送每个字符的整个序列中。
Alright, so another possibility,
好的，那么另一种可能是，
the sort of nasty problem here is
这里的令人讨厌的问题是
that uartwrite was holding a lock
uartwrite 持有锁，
at the time when it expected the interrupt routine to execute
在它希望中断进程发生的时候，
which is right here,
就在这里，
the only time when we really need the interrupt routine to execute is,
我们需要中断例程执行的唯一时间是，
is at this point here
就在这一点上，
otherwise it's okay to hold the lock,
其他时间持有锁也没有问题，
so another possibility would be to acquire the lock at the beginning,
所以另一种可能是在开始时获得锁，
because we need to protect our access to this shared variable done,
因为我们需要保护对这个共享变量 done 的访问，
but release it before the call to sleep,
但在调用 sleep 前释放它，
that gives the interrupt routine a chance to execute and set done to one
这给了中断例程机会执行并将完成标志设置为 1 ，
and then we'll just re-acquire it after sleep returns.
然后我们会在 sleep 返回后重新获取它。
So then we go back up to the top and check done again,
然后我们回到开始，再检查一遍，
we have the lock again.
我们又拿到了锁。
Alright, so let me actually modify my driver to do this.
好的，让我修改驱动程序来做这件事。
We'll see, yeah.
我们会看到，好的。
See what the consequences are.
看看后果是什么。
Alright.
好的。
So the sleep we're talking about where we want to,
所以我们所说的 sleep ，我们想要，
you can see this code actually does,
你可以看到，这个代码所做的，
acquire the lock at the very beginning and release it at the end
在开始时获取锁，并在结束时释放它，
and the interrupt routine also acquires and releases.
并且中断例程也获取和释放。
And the proposal is that we do two things,
建议是我们要做两件事，
one is, we're gonna, we're exploring is why my broken_sleep idea,
一个是，我们要探索为什么我的 broken_sleep 方法，
that only takes a single argument,
它只使用一个参数，
why that doesn't work.
为什么不能工作。
So the idea is that in order to make the locking workout right,
所以为了正确地进行使用锁，
we're gonna call broken_sleep alright,
我们调用 broken_sleep ，
but we're gonna release the lock here,
但是我们在这里释放锁，
and re-acquire it after sleep returns.
并在 sleep 返回后重新获得它。
And literally all this broken_sleep does is
这个 broken_sleep 所做的就是，
exactly what I wrote on my little whiteboard,
我写在白板上的东西，
namely, it sets the state to sleeping
也就是，它将状态设置为睡眠，
and sets the channel to this tx_chan argument,
并将信道设置为 tx_chan 参数，
then call swtch.
然后调用 swtch 。
Alright, let's see what happens.
好的，让我们看看会发生什么。
Oh, wow look at that, actually managed,
哦，看看这个，真的成功了，
so init is printing out, it's init starting message,
所以 init 正在打印，它是 init 启动消息，
and it actually managed to write a few characters
它成功地写下了几个字符，
and that seems to have hung.
但是似乎卡住了。
And it turns out that if I type a character,
如果我输入一个字符，
I'm going to type a period,
我输入一个句号，
by typing peri- period, output restarts,
通过输入句号，输出重新启动了，
maybe make more output I run ls,
也许我运行 ls 会产生更多的输出，
oops, ls also emitted a few characters and then stopped,
糟糕， ls 也输出几个字符，然后就停了，
but if I type something, I type type x,
但是如果我输入一些东西，我输入 x ，
will do restart ls, it'll keep going.
将重新启动 ls ，它将继续运行。
So.
所以。
What do you think is going on here?
你觉得这是怎么回事？
So you want to propose a theory.
所以你想提出一个理论。
The problem definitely has to do with the code that I just changed,
这个问题肯定与我刚刚更改的代码有关，
so what's happening.
那么发生了什么。
Alright, so what's going on here is
好的，这里的问题是，
that my new code releases the lock,
我的新代码释放了锁，
releases this lock at this point,
在这里释放了锁，
and then right here, the interrupt happens,
然后在这里，中断发生了，
because as soon as you release the lock,
因为一旦你释放锁，
first of all, the interrupts are re-enabled,
首先，会重新启用中断，
so in this CPU interrupts could happen,
所以，在这个 CPU 上，中断可能发生，
this is a multi-core machine,
这是一台多核心机器，
so actually interrupts can be taken on any core,
所以中断可以在任何核心上进行，
so almost certainly what's going on at this point that I've marked in the code is
所以几乎可以肯定，在这我标记的这一点上发生的是，
that on some other core, the uart interrupt is executing
在其他核心上， UART 中断正在执行，
and it's sitting in acquire,
它在 acquire 上，
waiting for this lock on some other core.
等待其他核心上的锁。
And so as soon as I release it,
所以当我释放了锁，
that other core is going to acquire the lock,
另一个核心将获得锁，
is going to see that the uart has completed sending the character,
会看到 uart 已经完成了字符的发送，
it's going to set this transmit done flag to one,
它将把这个传输完成标志设置为 1 ，
just great,
太棒了，
and then it's gonna call wakeup on tx_chan.
然后它使用 tx_chan 调用 wakeup 。
Which is also fine, except,
这也很好，除了，
because the writing thread is still executing between the release and the broken_sleep,
因为写入线程仍在释放和 broken_sleep 之间执行，
the writing thread hasn't gone to sleep yet,
写线程还没有进入睡眠，
so the wakeup that the interrupt routine calls
所以，中断例程调用的 wakeup
doesn't actually wakeup anything up,
并没有唤醒任何东西，
because nothing's yet gone to sleep on that channel.
因为没有什么东西睡眠在那个信道上。
And then, the writing thread will proceed to call this broken_sleep
然后，写入线程将继续调用这个 broken_sleep
which will, you know, set the state to sleeping and set the sleep channel,
这将将状态设置为睡眠，并设置睡眠信道，
but the interrupt has already happened and the wakeup has already been called,
但是中断已经发生，并且 wakeup 已经被调用，
so this sleep, nothing will ever wakeup,
所以这个睡眠，什么都不会唤醒，
because the wakeup already happened.
因为唤醒已经发生了。
This is called the lost wakeup problem.
这就是所谓的丢失唤醒问题。
Any questions about why or how this arises?
关于为什么或如何发生这种情况，有什么问题吗？
Yeah, is it always going to be the case,
是的，是不是一直都是这样，
that once something gets lost,
一旦东西丢失了，
once a wakeup gets lost,
一旦 wakeup 丢失了，
that on the next time, everything that's been buffered is just going to get dumped.
在下一次，所有被缓冲的东西都会被丢弃。
Well, it completely depends on the details of what's going on.
好的，这完全取决于发生了事情的细节。
In this case it's actually just us,
在这种情况下，它只是，
it's sort of accidental that,
这是一种意外，
me typing something caused the output to resume,
我输入某些内容会导致输出恢复，
me typing input caused the output get fixed
我输入会导致输出得到修复，
and the reason for that is that the uart has only one kind of interrupt,
原因是 uart 只有一种中断，
it makes it, it calls the same interrupt routine
它调用相同的中断例程，
whether for input to signal input and the signal completed output,
无论是信号输入还是信号完成输出，
so when I type something which is input,
所以，当我输入内容时，
the this uart interrupt routine gets called
会调用 uart 中断例程，
and the uart is thinking of is calling it just a signal that input has arrived,
而 uart 将其作为输入已经到达的信号，
but in fact the interrupt routine in xv6,
但实际上 xv6 中的中断例程，
you know looks for, you know notices that the you know the way this code happens to be written
注意到这段代码需要写入，
is that if the uart is ready to transmit another character,
如果 uart 准备好发送另一个字符，
it always calls wakeup,
它总是调用 wakeup ，
even though it's a while ago maybe I had already called wakeup,
虽然刚才可能已经调用过 wakeup 了，
so it's sort of accidental
所以这在某种程度上是偶然的，
that me typing characters caused us to get restarted
我输入字符导致重启，
and so sometimes if there are lost wakeups,
有时候，如果有丢失的唤醒，
sometimes they sort of fix themselves in this way, if you're lucky
幸运地话，有时它们会以这种方式修复自己，
and sometimes they don't,
而有时它们不会，
like if the uart had separate receive and transmit interrupt routines,
如果 uart 具有分开的接收和发送中断例程，
then there have been no getting out of this.
那就没有办法摆脱这件事了。
Does that answer your question?
这回答了你的问题吗？
Yes, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Okay.
好的。
So.
所以。
Yes, please go ahead.
好的，请继续。
What purpose does the tx_done bit serve?
tx_done 位的作用是什么？
Oh, the tx_done bit,
哦， tx_done 位，
or you mean this flag tx_done,
你是说这个标志 tx_done ，
it is simply a way for the interrupt routine to communicate to uartwrite.
这是中断例程与 uartwrite 通信的一种方式。
That a previously transmitted character is finished
先前传输的字符已经完成，
and it's OK for uartwrite to proceed to transmitting the next character,
uartwrite 可以继续传输下一个字符，
so it's a little piece of,
所以它是一小段，
just like a little communication flag from the interrupt routine to uartwrite.
中断例程到 uartwrite 的一个小通信标志。
Because if it it could like it would sleep
因为如果它会睡眠，
and then it would know that when it wakes up,
然后，当它醒来时，它会知道，
it's probably uart interrupted woke it up,
可能是 uart 中断唤醒了它，
so probably the tx_done bit like would have been set,
所以可能已经设置了 tx_done 位，
but if we didn't have it,
但如果我们没有它，
so I guess I'm saying that
所以我想我是说，
actually wakeup it should know that it's from uart interrupt.
wakeup 应该知道它是由 uart 中断引起的。
Okay, so is another way of phrasing your question,
好的，这是你提问的另一种方式，
how come there's this while loop here,
为什么这里会有个 while 循环，
instead of just.
而不是仅仅。
Okay, okay I think answer my question,
好的，我想回答了我的问题，
I think the answer to my question is,
我想问题的答案是，
because uart interrupt serve two purposes.
因为 uart 中断有两个目的。
Okay, yeah.
好的。
Yeah yeah yeah,
是的，
in general, did your answer your question is
一般说来，你的问题的答案是
sort of a specific instance of the more general answer that,
更笼统的回答的一个具体例子，
it's it just turns out to be not practical
事实证明这不是实际的，
to make sleeps and wakeups speed precise guaranteed precise,
让睡眠和唤醒保证精确，
that is that if sleep returns,
也就是说，如果 sleep 返回，
then for sure, whatever you're waiting for has happened.
那么可以肯定，无论你等待的是什么都已经发生了。
So, one example of this is that suppose we have two processes,
举个例子，假设我们有两个进程，
that are both trying to write that uart at the same time,
它们同时试图写入 uart ，
they're both in uartwrite and they can,
它们都在 uartwrite ，它们可以，
because after one writes a character, it'll sleep,
因为在一个写完一个字符之后，它会休眠，
releasing that turns out releasing the lock
释放锁，
and then the other one can enter that loop
然后另一个可以进入循环
and try to wait until uart not busy.
并等待，直到 uart 不忙。
And they both may both end up sleeping
它们可能最终都会睡眠，
and when an interrupt happens in the uart,
并且当 uart 中发生中断时，
can accept one more character,
可以再接受一个字符，
they'll both be woken up up,
它们都会被唤醒，
but only one should actually write the character.
但只有一个能真正写入这个字符。
And that this while loop.
这个 while 循环。
And in fact you'll see a while loop every sleep, in xv6 I believe,
事实上，我相信在 xv6 中的每个 sleep 都会出现 while 循环，
it's because this problem of,
就是因为这个问题，
you maybe woken up,
你可能醒来了，
but really somebody else sort of took the thing you were waiting for,
但实际上有人拿走了你等待的东西，
so you have to sleep again,
所以你得再睡眠一次，
this happens pervasively.
这种情况随处可见。
Okay.
好的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
I've got a question.
我有个问题。
So it looks like we only saw one lost wakeup,
好的。
because as soon as we pressed like a character,
因为只要我们按下键输入一个字符，
the rest of the output of the entire rest output came out,
剩下的输出就都出来了，
shouldn't we have seen multiple lost wakeups where,
我们不是应该看到多个丢失的唤醒吗，
why didn't happen again.
为什么没有再发生一次。
Oh, it did it did here,
哦，它是这样的，
let me let me run this,
让我来运行这个，
I'm going to run readme,
我要运行 readme ，
I'm going to cat README right,
我要执行 cat README ，
which is a couple thousand bytes,
这是几千字节，
so, oops, I had already typed something.
所以，糟糕，我已经输入一些东西了。
I guess we've got one character,
我想我们已经有一个字符，
I'm going to type a period,
我要输入一个句号，
we got a few more characters and then it hung up again.
我们又多了几个字符，然后它又卡住了。
I'm gonna take another period, another couple characters.
我要再输入一个句号，另外几个字符。
Each time I type a period that causes an interrupt for the input,
每次我输入句号，会引起输入的中断，
which then wakes up the process
然后唤醒这个进程，
and it could do a few more characters of wirtes then hangs again.
它可以再写出几个字符，然后再挂起来。
You know another lost wakeup.
另一个丢失的唤醒。
Yeah, just miss that, makes sense.
是的，错过了，有道理。
Yeah, so I'm typing period,
是的，所以我输入句号，
here I get a couple characters per lost wakeup,
每次丢失的唤醒都会得到几个字符，
because of the lost wakeup requires this coincidence,
因为丢失的唤醒需要这个巧合，
that the interrupt has already happened and was waiting to acquire the lock,
中断已经发生了，并且等待获取锁，
just that,
正是这样，
we get that coincidence a lot of the time, but not all the time.
我们经常会遇到这样的巧合，但并不总是。
Alright.
好的。
Okay so our goal then is to get rid of this lost wakeup problem,
好的，我们的目标是避免这个丢失唤醒的问题，
by somehow eliminating this window here,
通过消除这个窗口，
between the release of the uart_tx_lock,
在 release(&uart_tx_lock) 之间，
which we have to release,
我们必须释放它，
because the interrupt needs that lock,
因为中断需要这个锁，
so we know we have to release the lock.
所以我们必须释放锁。
But somehow we want to eliminate this window
但是，我们想要消除这个窗口
between when we release the lock and when the process actually marks itself as sleeping,
在释放锁和进程将自己标记为睡眠中，
so that the interrupts wakeup will see that the process is sleeping
所以中断的 wakeup 可以看到进程处于睡眠状态，
and actually wake it up and therefore not lose the wakeup.
真正唤醒它，而不会丢失唤醒。
So we've got to somehow close that window.
所以我们要消除这个窗口。
And to do that, we gotta make sleep's interface a little bit more complicated,
要做到这一点，会使睡眠接口变得更复杂，
so, go back to the original working sleep
所以，回到原来可以工作的 sleep ，
and I called a working sleep
我称为可工作的 sleep ，
and the way that people solve this problem is
人们解决这个问题的方式是
that sleep requires,
就是 sleep 需要，
even though sleep doesn't really know what you're waiting for,
即使 sleep 并不知道你在等什么，
it requires that you be waiting for something
它需要你在等待一些东西，
and furthermore that there be a lock
另外，还需要一个锁，
that protects whatever it is you're waiting for.
保护你等待的任何东西。
So it requires that there be a sleep condition,
所以它需要有一个睡眠状态，
which it doesn't really know about
它并不知道，
the sleep condition is that tx_done is equal to one,
睡眠状态是 tx_done 等于 1 ，
sleep doesn't know what the sleep condition is,
sleep 不知道睡眠状态是什么，
but it does it is requires, that there be a lock,
但是它需要有一个锁，
that protects the sleep condition, namely this uart_tx_lock
保护睡眠状态，也就是 uart_tx_lock ，
and the lock be locked when you check the condition,
当你检查状态时，是持有锁的，
that you hold the lock until you call sleep,
你一直持有锁直到调用 sleep ，
and that you pass the lock to sleep.
然后把锁传递给 sleep 。
And what sleep promises essentially at the interface level is
在接口层面上， sleep 保证的是
that it's gonna atomically put the process to sleep and release the lock
它会原子地使进程睡眠并释放锁，
as a sort of, at least it is an indivisible pair of actions,
作为一种，至少是一对不可分割的行动，
at least with respect to wakeup.
至少对于 wakeup 来说是这样的。
So, wakeup will never see this situation,
所以， wakeup 不会再看到这种情况，
which yeah you release the lock, but you know the process is not sleep,
你释放了锁，但是进程没有睡眠，
sleep makes the release of the lock and putting the process to sleep the atomic.
sleep 释放锁，进入睡眠状态是原子的。
And the rules for this is that there has to be, this has to be a condition,
这里的规则是必须有一个条件，
which has to be a lock protecting the condition,
必须有一个保护条件的锁，
the lock has to be held when you call sleep,
当你调用 sleep 时，必须持有锁，
you have to pass the lock to sleep,
你必须把锁传递给 sleep ，
and furthermore the lock has to be held, when you call wakeup.
另外，当你调用 wakeup 时，也必须持有锁。
This condition lock needs to be held when you call wakeup wakeup,
当你调用 wakeup 时，需要持有这个条件锁，
so these are rules, that the programmer had better follow,
所以这些都是程序员最好遵守的规则，
if they want to write correct code using sleep and wakeup.
如果想要使用 sleep 和 wakeup 编写正确的代码。
Alright.
好的。
So let's look at the sleep and wakeup,
让我们来看看 sleep 和 wakeup ，
trying to spot how they actually
试着发现它们是如何
use this extra little piece of information and these rules
使用这个额外信息和这些规则，
to avoid lost wakeups.
以避免丢失的唤醒。
So first I want to look at wakeup,
首先我想看一下 wakeup ，
wakeup not very surprising,
wakeup 并不令人惊讶，
it just runs through the entire process table,
它遍历整个进程表，
it locks every process,
它锁定每个进程，
remember that, after it's locked process,
还记得吗，在进程加锁之后，
you can't really look at a process at state with locking it,
你不能查看加锁进程的状态，
it locks each process,
它锁定每个进程，
if the process is sleeping,
如果进程处于睡眠状态，
and the channel that's sleeping for is the same channel that was passed to wakeup,
而且睡眠的信道跟传递给 wakeup 的信道一样，
then wakeup marks the changes the process of state to runnable
然后 wakeup 将进程的状态更改为可运行，
and then releases the process's lock.
然后释放进程的锁。
So no surprises here.
这里没有什么令人惊讶的地方。
We'll ignore my broken_sleep
我们忽略我的 broken_sleep ，
and instead look at sleep itself,
而是查看原来的 sleep ，
so here's the implementation of sleep,
这里是 sleep 的实现，
with now, this new lock argument.
现在，有这个新的 lock 参数。
So we know sleep has to reduce has to release that condition lock
所以我们知道 sleep 必须释放条件锁，
that its second argument,
这是它的第二个参数，
we know it has to release it,
我们知道它必须释放它，
because the you know the interrupt routine has to be able to acquire,
因为中断例程必须能够获取，
so we know there's going to be release of that lock somewhere inside sleep,
所以我们知道在 sleep 中某个地方释放锁，
and indeed here's the release of that lock,
实际上，这是那个释放锁的地方，
of course we're worried,
当然，我们会担心，
after we release the lock that at this very point,
在我们在这一点解锁之后，
wakeup might be called and might wake up this process,
可能会调用 wakeup 并且唤醒该进程，
so in order to might try to wake up this process,
所以为了唤醒这个进程，
but of course we haven't marked sleeping yet, right,
不过，我们还没有标记为睡眠，
so we cannot afford to have wakeup execute.
所以我们不能让 wakeup 执行。
Oops.
糟糕。
Have wakeup execute, right, after this release, even though we're releasing.
让 wakeup 在这个 release 之后执行，即使我们已经释放。
So in order to cause that not to happen,
所以为了避免这种情况发生，
before releasing the condition lock,
在释放条件锁之前，
sleep acquires the lock of the process that's going to sleep.
sleep 会获取将要睡眠的进程的锁。
If you recall, wakeup must be called with the condition lock held
如果你还记得， wakeup 必须在持有条件锁的情况下调用，
and it acquires the,
并且它获取，
if it's about to wakeup process,
如果要唤醒进程，
it first must wait to acquire that process's lock.
它首先必须等待获取进程锁。
So for the entire amount of time,
所以在这段时间里，
between when uartwrite between, before uartwrite checked the condition,
在 uartwrite 检查状态之前，
when we when we call sched here,
当我们在这里调用 sched 时，
this thread holds one or another of the condition lock and p->lock at all times.
这个线程始终持有条件锁和 p->lock 中的一个。
I just go back to uart, want to emphasize this,
我回到 uart ，想强调这一点，
uartwrite acquires the condition lock here
uartwrite 在这里获取状态锁，
and holds the condition lock all the way through to where it calls sleep,
并将状态锁一直持有到它调用 sleep ，
so it requires the condition lock,
所以它获得状态锁，
checks the condition with lock held,
在持有条件锁的情况下检查，
call sleep with the condition lock held,
在持有状态锁的情况下调用 sleep ，
so wakeup can't do anything now,
所以 wakeup 现在什么都做不了，
because it can not even allowed to call wakeup,
因为它甚至不允许调用 wakeup ，
until until the caller owns the condition locks,
直到调用者拥有条件锁，
so wakeup definitely not executing now,
所以 wakeup 肯定不是现在执行，
we still hold the lock, we call sleep,
我们还持有锁，我们调用 sleep ，
sleep releases the condition lock,
sleep 释放了条件锁，
but first acquires the process's lock.
但首先获取进程锁。
And if you remember,
如果你还记得，
oops,
糟糕，
wakeup, wakeup is called with the condition lock,
调用 wakeup 使用条件锁，
after we release it.
在我们释放它之后。
Sorry, after we release the condition lock,
抱歉，在我们释放条件之后，
wakeup can be called,
wakeup 可以被调用，
but wakeup won't look at the process
但是 wakeup 不会看到这个进程，
until it has the process lock which we hold.
直到它拥有我们持有的进程锁。
So okay, so wakeup is still not executing.
好的，所以 wakeup 仍然没有被执行。
Acquire the process lock, release the condition lock,
获取进程锁，释放条件锁，
while holding the process lock,
在持有进程锁的同时，
mark the process as sleeping on this particular channel
把进程标记为睡眠在这个信道上，
and then calls sched, which calls swtch right,
然后调用 sched ，它会调用 swtch ，
we still have the process lock, so wakeup still isn't doing anything,
我们仍然持有进程锁，所以 wakeup 没有做任何事情，
and if you remember,
如果你还记得，
the you know switching away from this thread to the scheduler thread
从这个线程切换到调度程序线程，
and the scheduler routine after it's called the swtch returns,
调度器例程在调用 swtch 返回后，
releases recently running process's lock.
释放最近运行的进程锁。
So at this point, after we're in the scheduler,
所以，在这里，在调度器中时，
wakeup can finally acquire p->lock for this process,
wakeup 可以获取这个进程的 p->lock ，
notice that it's sleeping and on this channel
注意到它睡眠在这个信道上，
and set its state to wakeup.
并将它的状态设置为唤醒。
So we guaranteed the effect of the rule
所以我们保证了规则的效果，
that you have to hold the condition lock when calling sleep,
当你调用 sleep 时，必须持有条件锁，
the fact that sleep knows about that lock
sleep 知道这个锁，
and release it only after requiring process p->lock
并且只有在获取 p->lock 之后才释放它，
and wakeup needing to hold both locks
而 wakeup 需要持有这两个锁，
in order to [think about] this process
为了[考虑]这个进程，
means that we can no longer lose a wakeup,
意味着我们不会再失去一个 wakeup ，
so we fix this lost wakeup problem.
所以我们解决了丢失唤醒的问题。
I realized a little bit involved,
我意识到有些[关联]，
any questions about what's going on here?
对于这里的事情，有什么问题吗？
Alright, well, feel free to ask questions at any time.
好的，请随时提问。
Alright, so we saw one, we saw this one, look at this one case,
好的，我们看到这个案例
in which were using sleep and wakeup in a way that avoids lost wakeups,
其中使用 sleep 和 wakeup ，并避免了丢失唤醒，
there's a bunch of others in xv6,
在 xv6 中还有很多其他的版本，
this particular one, the thing that we're waiting for the condition that we're waiting for,
特别是，我们在等待的条件，
you know is that interrupt has occurred,
是发生中断，
that has signalled that hardware is ready to do the next thing,
表明硬件已经准备好做下一件事，
there's also times when kernel code calls sleep
也有一些时候内核代码调用 sleep
in order to wait for a diff some other thread to do something,
为了等待其他的线程做一些事情，
which is not actually in the end conceptually different,
在概念上并没有什么不同，
but may feel a little bit different,
但可能感觉有点不同，
so in the pipe code, for example,
例如，在管道代码中，
if you look at piperead,
如果你查看 piperead ，
there's a bunch of junk here which you have to ignore,
这里有一堆东西，你可以忽略，
but the read system call on the pipe, ends up calling piperead,
但是管道中的的读系统调用，最终调用 piperead ，
there's a lock that protects the pipe
这里有一把锁保护管道，
and this is going to end up being the condition lock,
而这就是条件锁，
pipereed needs to wait until there's actually data buffered in the pipe,
piperead 需要等待，直到有数据缓冲在管道中，
and that condition is that there's data ready,
那个条件是数据就绪，
is nread or nwrite is greater than nread
是 nwrite 大于 nread ，
that is more bytes have been written than read,
也就是写入的字节多于读取的字节，
while that's not true, piperead sits in sleep, waiting for that condition,
当这不是真的， piperead 在 sleep 上，等待那种条件，
and passes in this pipe lock,
然后传入这个管道锁，
the condition lock that protects the condition into sleep,
条件锁到 sleep 中，
in order to protect against lost wakeup.
为了防止丢失唤醒。
So the reason why you might get lost wakeup is
所以你可能丢失唤醒的原因是，
that on a different core,
在不同的核心上，
a little farther up in the file,
在文件的上面一点，
on a different core,
在另一个核心上，
there's probably some other thread, just now calling pipewrite
可能有其他线程，刚刚调用了 pipewrite ，
and it's gonna add byte to the pipe buffer,
它会将字节添加到管道缓冲区，
and finally call the wakeup on the channel, that piperead waiting for
最后在 piperead 等待的信道上调用 wakeup ，
and you know we want to avoid the risk that between the reader checking,
我们想要避免读取者检查的风险，
there's, noticing there's no bytes to read and calling sleep,
注意到这里没有字节可读，并且调用 sleep ，
we do not want to pipewrite on another core to sleep in there,
我们不想让另一个核心上的 pipewrite 在这里睡眠，
and add bytes and wake us up, before we've even gone to sleep, right,
增加字节，唤醒我们，在我们进入睡眠之前，
would be a lost wakeup.
会是一次丢失的唤醒。
And this lock basically this lock
这把锁，
and the fact that sleep is careful about releasing it,
sleep 很小心地释放它，
prevent a writer from sleeping in,
防止写入者睡眠，
between the check of the condition and the sleep,
在检查条件和睡眠之间，
because the writer has to acquire the lock too.
因为写入者也必须获得锁。
And for those of you are,
对于你们来说，
the people asked about wrapping sleep and while loops,
有人问到关于包裹 sleep 和 while 循环的问题，
both pipereed and pipewrite are examples of sleep wrapped in a while,
pipereed 和 pipewrite 都是在一段时间内睡眠的例子，
so for example the, this is the loop that piperead waits for data to appear,
比如，这是 piperead 等待数据出现的循环，
waits for the buff pipe buffer to be non empty,
等待管道缓冲器为非空，
and the sleep is wrapped in a loop
这个 sleep 被包裹在一个循环中，
and again the reason is that,
再说一次，原因是，
there could be perfectly well be multiple processes reading the very same pipe
完全可以有多个进程读取相同的管道，
and so if a writer writes one byte to the pipe,
所以，如果写入着向管道写入一个字节，
so there's only one byte there,
那里只有一个字节，
the writer's going to call wakeup,
写入者会调用 wakeup ，
that's gonna wakeup all the multiple processes that were reading that pipe,
这将唤醒所有正在读取该管道的多个进程，
but there's only one byte in the pipe,
但是管道中只有一个字节，
and so one of those processes going to wakeup first, right,
所以其中一个进程会首先被唤醒，
it's going to come out of its sleep first.
它会首先从睡眠中醒来。
Actually, this reminds me,
这提醒了我，
there's another crucial thing I forgot to mention about sleep,
关于 sleep ，还有一件重要的事情我忘了说，
and that's that the last thing sleep does,
这是 sleep 做的最后一件事，
let's look at,
我们来看一下，
here's, here's the,,
这里是，
sorry,
抱歉，
here's the end of sleep,
这里是 sleep 的结尾，
the last thing sleep does is acquires the condition lock,
sleep 做的最后一件事是获取条件锁，
so you must call sleep with the condition lock held
所以，你必须在持有条件锁的情况下调用 sleep ，
and sleep re-acquires it before it returns.
sleep 在返回之前重新获取它。
Okay, so what that means is that,
好的，这意味着，
if there were a bunch of readers,
如果有一群读者，
there's one byte written to just return to a pipe
有一个字节被写入管道，
and a bunch of readers that all woken up,
有一群读者被唤醒，
one of them will succeed,
其中一个会成功，
one of the sleep, so one of the threads will succeed in acquiring this lock,
其中一个线程成功获取这个锁，
the others will be waiting and sleep, spinning waiting for the lock,
其他线程会等待并睡眠，旋转等待锁，
that one lucky process sleep will return,
一个幸运的睡眠进程将会返回，
it will come back to this check
它会回到这个检查上，
and you know p->nwrite is one larger than nread,
p->nwrite 比 nread 大 1 ，
so its data to read,
所以有数据可读，
it will fall out of the loop,
它会跳出循环，
will read the one byte
将读取一个字节，
and now there's nothing in the buffer,
现在缓冲区里什么都没有了，
release the lock, and return,
释放锁，然后返回，
and now the next thread that was woken up,
现在下一个线程被唤醒，
it's sleep will be able to re-acquire the condition lock,
它的 sleep 能够重新获得状态锁，
it's sleep will return, it will return, recheck the loop condition,
它的 sleep 将返回，重新检查循环条件，
but now nread is equal to nwrite,
但是现在 nread 等于 nwrite ，
and so that thread and any other thread waiting will go back to sleep.
所以这个线程和任何其他等待的线程将返回睡眠状态。
This is again just to reinforce,
这里再次强调，
why almost every, maybe every call to sleep
为什么几乎每次调用 sleep ，
has to be wrapped in a loop that re-checks the condition.
都必须包裹在一个重新检查条件的循环中。
Questions about the way sleep, pipes use sleep?
关于管道使用 sleep ，有什么问题吗？
Alright, the sleep and wakeup interface rules are a little bit complex.
好的， sleep wakeup 接口规则有点复杂。
Because you have to reveal a bit to sleep about what you're waiting for,
因为你需要透露睡眠时在等待什么，
you have to tell the lock and follow some rules,
你必须告诉锁，并遵守一些规则，
which is sometimes annoying.
这有时是令人讨厌的。
On the other hand, sleep and wakeup pretty flexible,
另一方面， sleep 和 wakeup 是相当灵活的，
partially, because they don't actually have to understand the condition itself,
部分原因是，它们不需要真正理解条件本身，
that just has to be a condition and be a lock,
只需要一个条件，一个锁，
there are other schemes that are somewhat higher level,
还有其他一些级别稍高的方案，
there's other coordination seems like the semaphore,
还有其他的协调，比如 semaphore ，
you read about in the reading for today,
你从今天的阅读材料中读到的，
in which the interface is slightly less complex,
其中接口不是那么复杂，
like the semaphores, you don't have to tell the semaphore about a lock,
比如信号量，你不必告诉信号量有关锁的信息，
and the caller to semaphore doesn't have to worry about lost wakeups,
并且信号量的调用者不必担心丢失唤醒，
internally the implementation of the semaphore,
信号量的内部实现，
again as you saw in the reading for today,
就像你们在今天的阅读材料中看到的，
the internal implementation of semaphores worries about lost wakeup.
信号量的内部实现担心丢失唤醒。
So, because the interface is specialized to these up down counters,
因为接口专用于这些递增递减计数器，
the need to deal with lost wakeup doesn't leak through into the interface.
处理丢失唤醒的需要不会显示到接口中。
So that semaphores are somewhat simpler,
所以信号量稍微简单一些，
although they're less general,
尽管它们不那么普遍，
if you don't, if you don't have a count,
如果你没有一个计数，
you're not waiting for count,
你不是在等待计数，
then semaphores are not necessarily going to be super helpful for you.
那么信号量不一定会对你非常有帮助。
So that that causes me to claim that sleep and wakeup a little more general.
所以，我说 sleep 和 wakeup 会更普遍一些。
Alright.
好的。
So with sleep and wakeup under our belts,
所以有了 sleep 和 wakeup 的经验，
I want to talk about one more kind of challenge that xv6 faces,
我想谈谈 xv6 面临的另一种挑战，
that's actually related to sleep and wakeup
它与 sleep 和 wakeup 有关，
and that's how to shut down threads.
那就是如何关闭线程。
Every threading system, the threads eventually need to exit
每个线程系统，线程最终都需要退出，
and we need to clean up their state, free their stack,
我们需要清理它们的状态，释放它们的堆栈，
on xv6, when a process exits,
在 xv6 上，当一个进程退出时，
we need to free its user memory
我们需要释放它的用户内存，
and free its page table and free its trapframe,
释放它的页表，释放它的 trapframe ，
mark the process the slot in the process table as reusable.
将进程表中的插槽标记为可重用。
So, these are sort of typical cleanup requirements is
所以，典型的清理要求是，
a bunch of stuff that has to be freed
一堆东西需要释放，
when threads exit or or killed.
当线程退出或被杀死时。
So, but there's two big problems that arise here,
但是这里有两个大问题，
with thread exit or killing threads,
与线程退出或杀死线程有关，
one is that we can't just reach out,
其一，我们不能仅仅伸手，
we can't usually just reach out and unilaterally destroy another thread,
我们通常不能伸手，单方面摧毁另一个线程，
the problem is that,
问题是，
other thread may actually be currently executing on another core
其他线程可能正在另一个核心上执行，
and using its stack
并使用其堆栈，
and maybe about to save its registers in its struct context or whatever,
可能要将寄存器保存在结构上下文中或其他什么，
the other thread if it's in the kernel, maybe holding locks,
另一个线程，如果它在内核中，可能持有锁，
it may be in the middle of some complicated update to a kernel data structure,
它可能正在对内核数据结构进行一些复杂的更新，
and if we simply somehow shoot down the thread
如果我们只是简单地强行中止它，
and stop it dead in its [tracks],
并停止，杀死在它的[轨道]上，
then it may have gotten halfway through a delicate update to some kernel data,
那么它可能已经完成了对一些内核数据的部分更新，
but we shot it down before it completed.
但我们在它完成之前强行中止了。
So, we can't afford any of those things to happen.
所以，我们不能承受这些事情发生。
Another problem is that even if a thread calls exit
另一个问题是，即使线程调用 exit ，
and sort of decided for its not killed,
不是决定要杀死，
but decided for itself that it wants to quit,
而是自己决定要退出，
it has resources that it uses while executes
它具有在执行时使用的资源，
like its stack, for example and its slot in the process table,
比如它的堆栈，和在进程表中的插槽，
and while it's still executing,
当它还在执行时，
it, it may not be able to free up the resources that is still using.
它可能不能释放还在使用的资源。
So we need a way for threads to,
所以我们需要一种方法让线程，
for those last few resources,
对于最后几个资源，
that are critical to execution to somehow be freed,
释放对执行至关重要的东西，
even though the thread needs them,
即使线程需要它们，
even just execute any code at all.
即使只是执行任何代码。
Okay, so keep these two problems in mind,
好的，记住这两个问题，
xv6 actually has two, two things,
xv6 实际上有两个东西，
that are related to shutting down threads or processes,
关于停止线程或进程，
one is exit and the other is kill.
一个是退出，另一个是杀死。
So let's look at exit first.
那么，我们先来看一下退出。
I'll look at the code for exit in proc.c,
我会查看 proc.c 中用于退出的代码，
this is what the exit system call calls.
这是 exit 系统调用所调用的。
And you know what exit has to do in the end,
退出最终要做的，
we know sort of from the outside from the interface,
从外部接口上了解，
that it's gonna free up the process memory and page tables,
它会释放进程内存和页表，
got to close its open files
关闭打开的文件，
and we also know that there's this wait call,
我们也知道有一个 wait 调用，
that the parent may be making, making
可能是父进程创造的，
and exit has to eventually cause the parent to be woken up as well
exit 最终也必须唤醒父进程，
and so we're going to look for all these things in the, in the exit code.
所以我们要在 exit 代码中查看这些东西。
So you can see some of this stuff,
所以你可以看到一些这样的东西，
like exit specifically closes the open files,
比如 exit 关闭打开的文件，
and this might actually be quite complex,
这可能非常复杂，
because the files or file system files closing them,
因为文件系统关闭文件，
actually involves things like reference counting.
涉及到比如引用计数的东西。
And we haven't gotten there yet,
我们还没到那一步，
but we'll see that,
但我们会看到，
this takes a fair amount of work.
这需要相当多的工作。
But a process goes ahead and closes when you call exit, closes its own files.
但是当你调用 exit 时，进程会继续并关闭它自己的文件。
And it also does something similar,
它也会做一些类似的事情，
it has a record of the current working directory,
它具有当前工作目录的记录，
which is what's changed when you call cd,
就是当你是使用 cd 时会变的目录，
and it needs to to sort of release that reference into the file system.
它需要在将该引用释放到文件系统中。
Then there's some other horrible stuff that happens,
然后，还有其他一些讨厌的事情发生，
that's related to the fact,
这与事实有关，
that if a process exits,
如果进程退出，
but it has children of its own,
但它有自己的子进程，
those children are inherited by the init process,
这些子进程由初始进程继承，
because as it turns out,
因为事实证明，
we'll see in a few minutes,
我们几分钟后就会看到，
that every process that exits, there has to be a corresponding wait from a parent,
每个退出的进程，都有来自父进程的对应的等待，
that actually finishes up some of the steps in exiting
这完成了退出过程中的一些步骤，
and so if I exit, my children they need to be waited for,
所以如果我退出，我的子进程需要等待，
I was their parent, I'm not going to wait for them,
我是它们的父进程，我不会等待它们，
because I've exited.
因为我已经退出了。
And so there's a stretch of code here
所以这里有一段代码，
and exit that is re-parenting the exiting processes children,
exit 重新给退出进程的子进程设置父进程，
so that their parents of init,
这样它们的父进程就是 init ，
which is process id one.
它的进程 ID 是 1 。
And then finally, a process wakes up its own parent,
最后，一个进程唤醒它的父进程，
which might be waiting and sleeping and wait,
可能在睡眠并等待，
and sets its state to the zombie state,
并将自己的状态设置为僵尸状态，
it turns out we haven't,
我们还没有，
but we'll see in a moment,
但我们稍后会看到，
but the process hasn't completely finished releasing all of its resources,
这个进程还没有完全释放所有的资源，
so it's not quite ready to be reused,
所以它没有准备好重新使用，
we want to end up in a position,
我们想要在一个位置结束，
where the process can be and all its state can be reused by a fork,
这个进程所有的状态可以由 fork 重用，
by some other fork that's unrelated right.
被另一个不相关的 fork 使用。
But we're not quite there yet,
但我们还没到那一步，
and we'll see why in a moment,
稍后我们会看到为什么，
we set the state to zombie,
我们把状态设为僵尸状态，
and then we're not done yet,
然后我们还没做完，
we haven't freed the process,
我们还没有释放这个进程，
we just jump into the scheduler,
我们只是跳到调度器中，
without having completely finished freeing our resources.
还没有完全释放我们的资源。
Okay.
好的。
So the story here continues,
所以这里的故事还在继续，
this point zombie process won't be run,
这里僵尸进程不会运行，
the scheduler only runs runnable processes,
调度器仅运行可运行的进程，
so this process isn't quite free,
这个进程没有释放，
because that would be state equals unused,
因为这是状态等于未使用，
but it's definitely not going to run again,
但它肯定不会再运行了，
because in state zombie,
因为在僵尸状态中，
so [] to the scheduler, scheduler now runs something else.
所以对于调度器，现在运行的是其他东西。
We knew from the sort of description of exit and wait,
我们从关于退出和等待的描述中知道，
in Unix that, if a process exits,
在 Unix 中，如果进程退出，
then its parent calls wait,
那么它的父进程调用 wait ，
the wait, that wait is going to return to signal to the parent,
wait 将返回信号通知父进程，
that one of its children is exited,
它的一个子进程退出了，
so we can look for the implementation of wait.
所以我们可以查看 wait 的实现。
Also, here is the big loop, this implementation of wait,
wait 的实现也是一个大的循环，
but really what's going on is that when a process calls wait,
但是当进程调用 wait 时，
it scans the process table,
它扫描进程表，
looking for processes whose parent is the current process,
查找父进程为当前进程的进程，
and in particular looking for processes,
特别是查找这样的进程，
whose parent is the current process and in state zombie,
它的父进程是当前进程并且处于僵尸状态，
that is they've gotten that far,
那就是它们走到这一步，
in in exit or almost finished exiting.
在退出或即将完成退出。
So now we found this called a wait to the wait system calls,
所以现在我们发现这调用 wait 系统调用，
found a child process that has exited.
找到已退出的子进程。
And, I don't know if you remember exit can return this 32 bit exit status,
我不知道你是否记得 exit 可以返回这个 32 位的退出状态，
so the parents of the next bunch of code collects that,
让父进程，剩下的代码可以收集这些信息，
and then it's the parent that calls freeproc,
然后是父进程调用 freproc ，
which does the final steps in freeing up process's resources.
完成了最后一部，释放进程的资源。
So we'll look at freeproc,
所以我们来看一下 freproc ，
and this is the final shutdown of stuff, that would be quite awkward,
这是最后一次关闭，这是很难处理的，
if the if the exiting process itself freed, while it was executing,
如果退出进程在执行时被释放，
it freezes trapframe, freeze the user page table,
它冻结 trapframe ，冻结用户页表，
and if we freed kernel stacks,
如果我们释放内核堆栈，
the process's, existing process's kernel stack would be freed here also,
现有进程的内核堆栈也将在这里释放，
but because of the stack guard, kernel stack stack guard page is,
但是由于堆栈保护页，
we don't actually ever turns out, we don't free, whenever free the kernel stacks,
我们没有释放内核堆栈，无论何时释放内核堆栈，我们都不会免费，
but all the stuff that would be a sort of potentially a pain to free in the exit,
但是这些东西在退出时都是一种潜在的痛苦，
while the exiting process is running is freed by the parent.
当正在运行的退出进程由父进程释放时。
One thing to notice here is that,
这里需要注意的一件事是，
wait, wait is not just for the convenience of parents,
wait 不仅是为了父进程方便，
that want to know when their when their children have exited,
它们想知道子进程什么时候退出，
wait is actually critical piece of the exit process
wait 实际上是退出进程的关键部分，
and you really in Unix, it's just a requirement,
在 Unix 中，这是一个需要，
that there be a wait that corresponds to every exiting process
wait 对应于每个退出的进程，
and that's really the reason why when a process exits its children
这就是为什么当进程退出其子进程时，
are sort of given away to init,
某种程度上给了 init ，
they're turning to init children,
它们成为了 init 的子进程，
when init does just calls wait in a loop,
当 init 在循环中调用 wait 时，
because every process has to be waited for,
因为每个进程都要等待，
so that the parent can call freeproc and finish freeing up resources
让父进程可以调用 freproc 并完成资源释放，
and then when it's completely done,
然后当它完全完成的时候，
it sets if the parents done freeing all the exit processes resources,
如果父进程完成释放所有退出进程资源，
sets that child state unused,
将子进程状态设置为未使用，
now fork and you know some future called a fork can reuse that process slot.
现在 fork 或将来调用 fork 可以重用该进程槽。
Any questions?
有什么问题吗？
Oh, I have a question about sleep,
哦，我有个关于 sleep 的问题，
so in sleep where we are.
所以在 sleep 中，我们。
Yeah, so when we are,
是的，当我们，
oh, sorry, not sleep, exit.
哦，抱歉，不是 sleep ，而是 exit 。
I want say exit, yeah.
我想说的是 exit ，是的。
Yeah, so why are we,
是的，为什么我们，
why are we grabbing original parent before we reparent,
为什么我们要在重新分配父进程前[抓住]最初的父进程，
is that necessary.
这是必须的吗。
This is [] code, that's wrestling with the possibility
这是[]代码，处理一种可能性，
that a process and its parent may exit at the same time.
进程和父进程同时退出的情况。
And there's some,
还有一些，
even though ordinarily, just nothing interesting going on process exits,
尽管最初的，不关心进程退出，
its parent waits for it, everything's fine,
它的父进程等待它，一切都很好，
but it could be that parent, that a process exits
但它可能是进程退出的父进程，
and its parent process exits at the same time
并且它的父进程同时退出，
and so while we're trying to wake up our parent to tell we've exited,
所以当我们试图唤醒父进程，告诉它我们已经退出时，
that parent is itself exiting.
那个父进程已经退出了。
And a lot of this code here,
这里有很多这样的代码，
which I feel I kind of understood a year ago,
我觉得我一年前是明白的，
but don't any longer understand,
但现在不再明白了，
is about taking care of this rare case of concurrent exits of a parent and child.
是关于处理这种罕见的父进程和子进程同时退出的情况。
And if it weren't for that,
如果不是因为这个，
it would all be extremely straightforward,
那么这一切都会非常简单，
a parent, the process would have a parent
进程有一个父进程，
and it would just wake up its parent at this point.
它只需要在这里唤醒它的父进程。
And, we wouldn't,
而且，我们不会，
it were for concurrent exits a parent and child.
它是对于父进程和子进程同时退出的。
The child could just wake up its parent period.
子进程可以唤醒父进程。
Okay, I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Sorry to not really be explaining here.
抱歉，我不能解释更多了。
I have a quick question,
我有一个简短的问题，
so why are we setting the process state to zombie after we wake up the parent,
为什么我们要在唤醒父进程之后将进程状态设置为僵尸状态，
we want to do that before.
我们想在此之前这么做。
Oh yeah, it turns out because we've acquired the,
哦，是的，是因为我们获得了，
the existing processes that required its own process lock,
现有进程获取了自己进程锁，
the parent can't look at this process.
父进程不能看到这个进程。
And we've acquired our own lock here
我们在这里获得了自己的锁，
and then we're going to call sched,
然后我们调用 sched ，
the parent, is parents wait acquires p-> requires the child's lock, which is p->lock
父进程需要等待子进程的锁，也就是 p->lock ，
and so that means that between this acquire
这意味着在这个获取
and when after we call sched and the scheduler thread releases this p->lock,
和我们调用 sched 之后，调度器线程释放 p->lock 之间，
the parent can't look at this process in this block of code.
在这块代码中，父进程不能看到这个进程。
Okay.
好的。
So the order of this stuff doesn't matter,
所以这些东西的顺序并不重要，
indeed if we didn't have the lock up,
事实上，如果我们没有锁，
it's possible some other.
也有可能其他的。
Well, in most situations, no order would work if we didn't hold the lock.
在大多数情况下，如果我们不持有锁，任何顺序都不会起作用。
Anyway, yeah because we hold a lock, that the order doesn't matter,
不管怎样，是的，因为我们有一把锁，顺序无关紧要，
because the parent can't look.
因为父进程看不到。
That makes sense.
理解了。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, so the trick here is the trick I wanted to emphasize was that,
好的，我想强调的技巧是，
to a great extent, actually the child doesn't,
在很大程度上，子进程没有，
in the end, the child doesnt free all its resources,
最终，子进程并没有释放所有的资源，
because it can't, because it's still using the whole executes
因为它不能，因为它仍在执行，
and instead some other thread, namely the parent
取而代之的是一些其他线程，也就是父线程
does the freeing of the delicate resources that are required for execution,
来释放执行所需的资源，
so that's sort of a trick
所以这是一种技巧，
to allow us to that greatly simplify exit.
让我们极大地简化了退出。
Okay, the last thing I want to look at is kill,
好的，我最后要看的是 kill ，
so that you know the kill system call,
你知道 kill 系统调用，
one process in Unix can call that make the kill system call,
在 Unix 中，可以调用 kill 系统调用，
passes the process id of a different process
传递另一个进程的进程 id ，
and the goal is that
目标是，
that should cause that other process, the target process to stop executing.
导致另一个进程，目标进程停止执行。
And if we're not careful,
如果我们一不小心，
you know this risks especially if other processes executing in the kernel,
这有风险，特别是如果内核中执行的其他进程，
this risk is probably mentioned a few minutes ago,
这个风险可能在几分钟前就提到了，
where gosh that you know the kernel thread of the process you're trying to kill
你想杀死的进程的内核线程，
might might in the middle of updating something,
可能正在更新一些东西，
you know updating the file system, creating a file, for example
比如，更新文件系统，创建文件，
and we can't just kill it dead on the spot,
我们不能直接杀死它，
because that would leave some delicate multi step operation only halfway completed.
因为这将使一些多步骤操作只完成一半。
Now, so we know that kill can't really just stop the target process,
现在，我们知道 kill 不能真正停止目标进程，
and indeed in xv6 and the Unix as well,
事实上，在 xv6 中，在 Unix 中也是如此，
kill does almost absolutely nothing,
kill 几乎不会做什么事情，
it scans the process table looking for the target process id
它扫描进程表，查找目标进程 id ，
and just sets this flag in that process's process structure,
只是在进程的进程结构中设置这个标志，
and also, if it was sleeping, calls to be runnable,
而且，如果它处于睡眠状态，调用到可运行，
so to wake up from sleep,
从睡眠中唤醒，
but all it does is set this flag,
它所做的就是设置这个标志，
it doesn't stop the other process from executing or anything like it.
它不会停止另一个进程的执行或任何类似的操作。
Kill itself very gentle,
kill 是非常温和的，
the game is that,
游戏是，
the target process at points in the kernel code
目标进程在内核代码中，
where it would be safe to stop executing,
在那里会安全地停止执行，
the other process checks its own killed flag,
另一个进程检查它自己的终止标志，
and if it's set,
如果设置了，
the other process sort of voluntarily exits, calls this exit function
其他进程会自动退出，调用 exit 函数，
and you can see some of those points at trap.c,
你可以在 trap.c 上看到其中的一些点，
in fact you can see all the points trap.c,
实际上，你可以在 trap.c 中看到所有的点，
so if we're in usertrap
所以，如果我们在 usertrap 中，
in a system call, before actually executing the system call,
在实际执行系统调用之前，
if the process has already been killed
如果进程已被终止，
or if kill has been called for this process,
或者如果在这个进程调用了 kill ，
then the process calls exit and goes away.
然后进程调用 exit 并离开。
And this is a point in the kernel where it's not holding any locks,
这是内核中的一个点，没有持有任何锁，
it's not in the middle of doing anything,
它没有在做任何事情，
and so it's completely safe for the process to just quit and call exit.
所以，进程是安全的，只需退出并调用 exit 。
And there's a similar check, at the end of usertrap.
在 usertrap 末尾有一个类似的检查。
So after a system call, the process also checks if it's being killed
所以，在系统调用之后，进程还会检查它是否被终止，
and indeed this code here executes,
实际上，这段代码会执行，
even if the process is interrupted by an interrupt,
即使进程被中断打断，
so for example the timer interrupt goes off,
比如，定时器中断关闭，
then this code will execute
然后，这段代码会执行，
and we'll see that the process has been killed
我们会看到这个进程已被终止，
and then the process will exit.
然后这个进程将会退出。
And so what that means is
所以，这意味着，
that the what kill means, kill the meaning of kill,
kill 的意思是，
the effective kill is not exactly stop the other process right now,
kill 的作用不是直接停止其他进程，
it's much more like,
而更像是，
well you know if the process other processes in user space,
如果用户空间中的其他进程，
then the next time it makes a system call,
然后下一次它进行系统调用时，
it will exit
它会退出，
or the next time a timer interrupt goes off
或者下一次定时器中断发生时，
while executing user code in the target process,
当目标进程执行其他用户代码时，
if it's interrupted by a timer interrupt or some other interrupt,
如果它被定时器中断或其他中断中断，
then it will also exit.
那么它也会退出。
So there might be a significant delay,
所以，这里可能会有明显的延迟，
between when one process calls kill and when the other process actually exits.
在一个进程调用 kill 和另一个进程实际退出。
And that's just the way it is.
事情就是这样的。
There's a sort of intermediate question
虽然有一个中间问题，
though if the process is not in use, it's own user space,
如果进程没有在自己的用户空间，
but is in the middle of a system call,
而是在进行系统调用中，
and it's killed,
它被杀死，
do we need to do anything special?
我们需要做些什么特别的事情吗？
The reason why this may come up is,
可能会出现这种情况的原因是，
suppose the process is reading from the console, right,
假设进程正在从控制台读取，
you know reading for the next character you type,
读取你输入的下一个字符，
you may not type another character until tomorrow.
你可能知道明天都不会输入另一个字符。
And it would be nice if when you kill the process,
这是可以的，如果你终止进程，
it actually went away before tomorrow.
它实际上在明天之前就消失了。
And for that reason, in a number of points in xv6
所以，在 xv6 的很多点上。
in which a process is sleeping,
当进程在睡眠中，
xv6 actually arranges that,
xv6 会安排，
if it's killed while sleeping in the kernel,
如果它在内核中睡眠时被杀死，
it will actually exit.
它实际上会退出。
So, let me show you the machinery for that,
让我来展示一下这个机制，
the first thing to look at is in kill itself.
首先要看的就是 kill 本身。
You can see that if the target process is sleeping,
你可以看到，如果目标进程处于睡眠状态，
then kill will set state to runnable
然后 kill 会将状态设置为可运行，
and that'll mean that even if it had called sleep,
这意味着即使它调用了 sleep ，
the scheduler will now run it
调度器现在也会运行它，
and it will simply return from sleep.
它会简单地从睡眠中恢复过来。
And so let's look at a place where that actually matters,
所以让我们来看看一个真正重要的地方，
in the pipe code, if a process is in sleep waiting to read a pipe,
在管道代码中，如果进程处于睡眠状态，等待读取管道，
and it's killed, kill set to runnable return from sleep,
它被杀死， kill 设置从睡眠到可运行，
go back to the top of this loop,
回到这个循环的顶部，
probably if there was no data in the pipe,
如果在管道中没有数据，
before the pi-, still be no data in the pipe,
在管道中仍然没有数据，
and now piperead at least checks whether the process has been killed
现在， piperead 会检查进程是否已被终止，
and if it has been killed,
如果它已经被杀死，
instead of sleeping again,
不是再次睡眠，
the piperead will return return an error, doesn't really matter,
piperead 会返回一个错误，并不重要，
but we're returning to is this syscall,
但我们要回到的是这个系统调用，
since we're in a system call,
因为我们在系统调用中，
where pipe really returns to in the end is returns from the system call,
管道最终返回系统调用，
and then usertrap checks p->killed again
然后 usertrap 再次检查 p->killed ，
and will now exit.
现在可以退出了。
So for, sleeps,
所以，对于 sleep 来说，
that we know it's okay to just bail out of when a process is killed,
我们知道[逃脱]是可以的，当它被杀死，
those loop's check the killed flag,
这些循环检查 killed 标志，
but there are also sleeps where it would not be okay,
但也有 sleep 这样是不可以的，
for a process to quit,
对一个要退出的进程，
if it's killed in that sleep.
如果它在睡眠状态下被杀死。
So, for example if a process is in the middle of updating the file system on disk
比如，如果某个进程正在更新磁盘上的文件系统，
to create a new file
要创建新文件，
that is it bad time,
现在不是时候，
even if it's sleeping waiting for the disk,
即使它在睡眠等待磁盘，
that's a bad time for a process to just decide to quit,
对于一个进程来说，现在不是退出的时候，
because it's been killed,
因为它已经被杀死，
we want to finish the complete file system operation,
我们要完成完整的文件系统操作，
and only then have the process exit,
只有在那时进程才可以退出，
and so you can see this,
所以你可以看到这个，
we've looked at this,
我们已经看过了，
but I'll show you in the disk driver.
但我将在磁盘驱动程序中展示。
An example of a sleep loop,
睡眠循环的一个例子，
that doesn't check killed,
不会检查 killed ，
look at that,
看那里,
so here we are, this is the sleep
所以在这里，这是 sleep ，
in which they process waits for the disk to finish reading a disk block,
进程等待磁盘完成读取磁盘块，
and it absolutely doesn't check killed,
它绝对不会检查 killed ，
because it wants to finish it,
因为它想要完成它，
maybe in the middle of creating a file,
也许在创建文件的过程中，
which involves multiple disk reads and writes,
涉及多个磁盘读取和写入，
want to finish the entire file system operation,
想要完成整个文件系统操作，
the entire system call
整个系统调用，
and only then check p->killed and exit.
然后才检查 p->killed 并退出。
Questions about anything?
有什么问题吗？
I have a question,
我有一个问题，
about why kill allowed in the way it it,
为什么 kill 允许以这种方式，
why wouldn't the process kill all the other processes
为什么进程不会杀死所有其他的进程，
if you can run, oh, by itself.
你可以自己运行。
Well, you know you do that MIT on a Athena time sharing machine
你知道，如果你在麻省理工学院的 Athena 分时机器上这样做，
will probably kick you out of school.
可能会把你赶出学校。
Right, but why is it allowed.
是的，但是为什么允许这样做呢？
It's allowed in xv6, because xv6 is a toy operating system,
在 xv6 允许，因为 xv6 是一个玩具操作系统，
that it just the,
它只是
anything that has to do with like permissions just doesn't exist in xv6,
在 xv6 中，任何与权限有关的东西都不存在，
in Linux or a real operating system,
在 Linux 或真正的操作系统中，
every process has a user id,
每个进程都有一个用户 id ，
that corresponds to the more or less to the human user who's executing the process
对应于执行该进程的人类用户，
and some system calls use the user id of the process
一些系统调用使用进程的用户 id
to kind of check what is the process allowed to do this,
检查允许哪些进程执行此操作，
and so in Linux, you would see a extra check here,
所以在 Linux 中，你会在这里看到一个额外的检查，
that said that the calling process has to have the same user id,
就是调用进程必须具有相同的用户 id ，
as the process is trying to kill,
与想要杀死的进程一样，
otherwise it's not allowed.
否则是不允许的。
And that, at least in a time sharing context,
而且，至少在分时背景下，
we have multiple users
我们有多个用户，
and we don't want them to kill each other's processes,
我们不希望他们杀死彼此的进程，
that's more or less sufficient to keep people from
这或多或少可以防止人们，
make it hard for people to kill other people's processes.
使其难以杀死其他人的进程。
Okay I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Does init process ever exit?
init 进程是否会退出？
Let me check.
让我找找。
Yes, if fork fails, exit,
是的，如果 fork 失败，退出，
however the real answer to the question is no,
然而，这个问题的真正答案是否定的，
the intent is that init never exit,
其目的是 init 永远不会退出，
they just sit in this loop
它们只是在这个循环中，
and what is doing is calling wait over and over again,
一遍又一遍地调用 wait ，
if init exits, I think that's a fatal error in the system will crash.
如果 init 退出，我认为这是系统中的致命错误，系统将崩溃。
There's code somewhere in the kernel, it says, may be in exit.
内核中的某个地方有代码，可能在 exit 中。
Just check exit.
检查一下 exit 。
Yeah, here we are, exit, at the beginning of exit,
是的，在这里， exit ，在 exit 的开头，
if it looks like the current process is the init process, it's a panic.
如果当前进程是是 init 进程，那就是一个 panic 。
Because, this system would eventually [] to a halt,
因为，这个系统最终会陷入停顿，
if there were no init,
如果没有 init ，
because then there would be nothing collect,
因为这样就没有什么东西收集，
nothing to call wait on these exiting processes
没有什么东西调用 wait 对于那些退出的进程，
and nothing to complete the freeing of the processes
并且没有任何东西可以完成进程的释放，
and gradually we run out of processes,
慢慢地，我们的进程耗尽了，
and then that would be some other error.
那就是另一个错误了。
We have to have init.
我们必须有 init 。
So the real answer is that no,
所以真正的答案是不，
it really can't be allowed to exit,
它确实不能被允许退出，
better not exit.
最好不要退出。
Okay.
好的。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Um, it's another question,
这是另一个问题，
so, we haven't really talked about much in this class yet,
所以，我们在这节课上还没有谈到太多，
but look what happens or what needs to happen to shut down the OS.
但看看关闭操作系统会发生什么或需要发生什么。
Got unplugged.
被拔掉电源。
Okay.
好的。
Yeah.
是的。
Yeah, this is very complex,
是的，这很复杂，
and it depends on what you're running,
这取决于你运行的是什么，
if you're, if the operating if the machine is currently doing nothing,
如果你在，如果机器当前什么都不做，
well, part of the answer the question is
好的，这个问题的部分答案是，
that the file system ends up being,
文件系统最终，
because the file system is permanent,
因为文件系统是永久性的，
you know the file system is carried over from reboot to reboot.
文件系统会从一个重启到另一个重启。
We need to leave the file system in good shape,
我们需要让文件系统保持良好的状态，
so if we were in the middle of some update to the file system,
所以，如果我们正在对文件系统进行某些更新，
like creating a file,
比如创建文件，
then we want to shut the system down or the power fails or something,
然后我们想要关闭系统或者停电之类的，
we absolutely need a strategy to make sure that,
我们绝对需要一个策略来确保，
even though we were in the middle of some complex update to the file system,
尽管我们正在对文件系统进行一些复杂的更新，
that we don't leave it in the file system in a state,
我们不会把它留在文件系统中，
we don't expose any broken invariance in the on disk file system structures,
我们不会在磁盘文件系统结构中公开任何损坏的不变量，
because the files is really just a data structure, that lives on disk.
因为文件实际上只是一种在磁盘上的数据结构。
So there's like a lot of,
所以有很多这样的，
that's sort of machinery involved in making sure that
一些机制来确保，
if you shut down or the power fails or who knows what that,
如果你关机了或者停电了或者谁知道会发生什么，
the disk can, that we can recover the file system on disk.
我们可以恢复磁盘上的文件系统。
For the rest of, it's not for that,
对于其他，不是为了这个，
then, whether you have to do anything special to shutdown
那么，你是不是要做一些特殊的事情来关机，
depends on what processes you're running,
取决于你正在运行什么进程，
if you're running some important server, a database server,
如果你正在运行某个重要的服务器，一台数据库服务器，
that a lot of other computers depend on and use over the network,
许多其他计算机依赖，并从网络上访问，
who knows, the answer may be that you just cannot be allowed to shut down,
答案可能是你不被允许关机，
because you're providing a service that's critical to a bunch of other computers.
因为你提供的服务对很多其他计算机都很重要。
If your computer is not doing much of anything.
如果你的计算机没有执行任何操作。
Then you can just turn it off
那你就可以把它关掉，
and it will stop executing
它会停止执行，
and there's not much to do,
没有什么可做的，
really, may be the answer to your question is,
真的，也许你问题的答案是，
if you want to shut down the computer,
如果你想关闭计算机，
make sure the file system is in good shape
确保文件系统状态良好，
and then stop executing instructions and that's fine.
然后停止执行指令，就好了。
Good.
好的。
That makes sense, yeah, thank you.
有道理，是的，谢谢。
Anything else?
还要别的吗？
Oh, sorry, I have another question,
哦，抱歉，我还有一个问题，
so what is this semaphore interface.
那么这个信号量接口是什么。
About p and v.
关于 p 和 v 。
So just two, just those two functions?
所以，只有这两个函数？
Um, yeah.
嗯，是的。
Yeah, xv6 doesn't have semaphores really,
是的， xv6 实际上没有信号量，
but you know the books semaphores, I think it's just p and v,
但是书中的信号量，我想它只是 p 和 v ，
there are two methods, you have a semaphore object has two methods p and v.
信号量对象有两个方法 p 和 v 。
Okay, I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Sure.
好的。
Anything else?
还要别的吗？